<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>current | Dávalos Lab</title>
    <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/tag/current/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://lmdavalos.github.io/tag/current/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>current</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/icon_hud44501404c914d67889d8518d1a662c7_303770_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>current</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/tag/current/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The molecular basis of viral tolerance in bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/molecular_basis_viral_tolerance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/molecular_basis_viral_tolerance/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the Impact of Narcotrafficking on Amazon Forest Conversion and Land Grabbing</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/fulbright_amazonia/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/fulbright_amazonia/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Path to Climate Stability: Unleashing the Power of Azolla for Carbon Sequestration</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/azolla_carbon_capture/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/azolla_carbon_capture/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We propose to explore Azolla as a solution to present-day scalable carbon capture by linking it with the Nitro-Oxidation Process (NOP) for sequestration. While the NOP has been found to be effective at producing nanocelluloses for application ranging from soil amendments to water filters, its potential for stabilizing carbon has yet to be evaluated. Because the NOP separates carbon in cellulose from effluents that contain remaining elements, this process can enable efficient phosphorus (and other nutrient element) recycling. This dual potential for carbon storage and nutrient recovery, however, remains to be tested. Demonstrating maximal carbon capture rates, and the suitability of the NOP to both stabilize Azolla biomass and reuse nutrients will make this project competitive with a diverse suite of potential funders.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrated mechanisms of environment-host-virome interactions</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/integrated_mechanisms_environment_host_virome/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/integrated_mechanisms_environment_host_virome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Human disruption of the environment is thought to play a central role in disease emergence in wildlife populations by reducing the availability of foods and refuge that animals rely upon, thereby stressing the animals and making them more susceptible to viruses. However, the mechanisms governing relationships among the environment, the wildlife host, and the viral communities they support are poorly known. To address this problem, the project will take advantage of a single cohesive wild system of Egyptian fruit bats (Rousettus aegyptiacus) to sample animals of different sex, age, and reproductive condition from caves that support different numbers of bats, are subject to variable levels of hunting, and are surrounded by different qualities of foraging habitat and hence food resources. Using each individual bat as the unit of observation, analyses will aim to relate landscape resources, and individual condition and immunity to viral profiles, thus answering three key questions: (1) how do host abundance, reproduction, age, and condition differentially or interactively influence viral diversity; (2) how do molecular immune mechanisms respond to environmental and physiological stressors in wild populations; and (3) how do gene expression profiles and viral infection influence one another in the wild? The results should allow links to be discerned that connect environmental gradients of human disturbance to virome diversity via organismal conditions, thereby providing essential new information for understanding disease dynamics in the wild, modeling risks, and thus preventing the next pandemic. Moreover, the project’s integrated and mechanistic systems approach to studying fundamental processes in disease emergence is expected to be generalizable across taxa at the human-wildlife disease interface.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Co-evolution of viruses with host genome-editing enzymes in bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/biochemical_and_genomic_characterization_apobec/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/biochemical_and_genomic_characterization_apobec/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Global Union of Bat Diversity Networks (GBatNet)</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/global_bat_net/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/global_bat_net/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
