<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dávalos Lab</title>
    <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://lmdavalos.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Dávalos Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/icon_hud44501404c914d67889d8518d1a662c7_303770_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Dávalos Lab</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Newly assembled pocket gopher genomes can facilitate conservation management of biodiversity</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_newly_assembled_pocket_gopher_genomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_newly_assembled_pocket_gopher_genomes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bat genomes illuminate adaptations to viral tolerance and disease resistance</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_reference_quality_bat_genomes_illuminate_adaptations_viral/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_reference_quality_bat_genomes_illuminate_adaptations_viral/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic metabolic and molecular changes during seasonal shrinking in Sorex araneus</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/preprint_molecular_mechanisms_seasonal_brain_shrinkage_regrowth_sorex/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/preprint_molecular_mechanisms_seasonal_brain_shrinkage_regrowth_sorex/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symposium: Climate Change in the Amazon</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/24-12-06-fulbright-amazonia-symposium/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/24-12-06-fulbright-amazonia-symposium/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our symposium on Climate Change in the Amazon took place from 12:30-5:30 pm on &lt;strong&gt;December 6, 2024&lt;/strong&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://iacs.stonybrook.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IACS&lt;/a&gt; Conference Room. Below the fold for a synopsis!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On December 6, 2024, we gathered at the Institute for Advanced Computational Science, for a whole afternoon of conversations with the Stony Brook University community on climate change in the Amazon. But this was not just a symposium, we also had an Ask-Me-Anything session with students. Students asked how our experiences informed our careers, how to persist despite the herculean work of mitigating and adapting to climate change, and about the elements of our research with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fulbrightprogram.org/amazonia/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fulbright Amazonia&lt;/a&gt;. Students were also interested in how we established and maintained throughout the years a relationship with traditional communities in the Amazon region and how, as scientists, we gained the skills to work with these communities. They also asked how we could keep having hope and not give up on our research despite the many obstacles we face. Persistence, openness, and a willingness to listen were all part of the answer to student questions. Experts from the Amazon and beyond came together with the community to present their research and hold conversations about our global future!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

















&lt;div class=&#34;gallery-grid&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-beon-0&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-0/IMG_4028.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Dr. Ribeiro giving her presentation on disseminating scientific knowledge about climate change for extractivist communities in Acre, Brazil.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-0/IMG_4028_hu754495b3d2727eb324b7b92307768596_198366_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Dr. Ribeiro giving her presentation on disseminating scientific knowledge about climate change for extractivist communities in Acre, Brazil.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-beon-0&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-0/IMG_4033.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Dr. Iñamagua gave his talk on mitigating Climate Change through productive landscapes design, here showing the many mammals of these productive ecosystems.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-0/IMG_4033_hub732e85e03ec3dc99bad9b6e5b56d756_270060_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Dr. Iñamagua gave his talk on mitigating Climate Change through productive landscapes design, here showing the many mammals of these productive ecosystems.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-beon-0&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-0/IMG_4035.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Dr. Selaya presented on detangling factors impacting forest health in Southwestern Amazonia.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-0/IMG_4035_hu8f67ce2f1cc861549b0fcadb035815c8_190314_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Dr. Selaya presented on detangling factors impacting forest health in Southwestern Amazonia.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, &lt;a href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/author/sabina-ribeiro/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof. Sabina Ribeiro&lt;/a&gt; shared her insights on disseminating knowledge of climate change to extractivist communities in Acre, Brazil. Her work with people living and working at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.mongabay.com/2020/04/in-famed-chico-mendes-reserve-brazil-nut-harvesters-fight-to-save-the-forest/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Chico Mendes Extractivist Reserve&lt;/a&gt; (yes, it is named after &lt;strong&gt;the&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bbc.com/news/av/stories-51021984&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Chico Mendes&lt;/a&gt;) revealed pamphlets and radio are outdated means of communication. Instead, social media and WhastsApp groups are the best means to reach them. Though many are aware of climate change, few understand why it is happening or how their actions can help to mitigate or adapt to it locally. Besides more intense droughts, workdays have become shorter as temperatures have risen. By discovering how to best reach rubber tappers and extractivists as a whole, Ribeiro aims to increase environmental awareness to help the conservation of the forests in the reserve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www2.ucuenca.edu.ec/idrhica/es/juan-pablo-inamagua/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof. Juan Pablo Iñamagua&lt;/a&gt; showed his work on designing productive landscapes in Cuenca, Ecuador. Although most expect productive landscapes to detract from the forest, Iñamagua studies agroforestry, which maintains some forest cover side-by-side with crops. As it turns out, there are many laws in the books to help promote agroforestry, including the unique Rights of Nature enshrined in the Ecuadorian constitution. Yet, these environmental laws are seldom enforced. In the south of Morona Santiago province, clearings on slopes for pasture implementation promote destructive landslides, so that adopting agroforestry can mitigate not just climate change but also landslides. He has also found a thriving mammalian community of wild native cougars, tapirs, and deer in these landscapes, documenting their value for biodiversity as well. His vision for productive yet sustainable landscapes is a key step in tackling climate challenges in the Amazon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To close out the first panel, &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=o-Tw_gUAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Galia Selaya&lt;/a&gt; presented her work to discover the factors behind forest health in Pando, Bolivia. While in recent years the tropical rainforests of Bolivia have been under siege from fires to clear land for agriculture, the Pando department has been spared in comparison. This is in part because many people in Pando rely on Brazil nuts, which require standing forests to thrive. Nevertheless, satellite imagery she analyzed shows fluctuations from year-to-year. Some of it is natural, such as synchronous native bamboo stands that wilt all at once, but much vegetation change extends outward from roads and agricultural lands. Her research thus highlighted key drivers of forest health and potential solutions for restoration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

















&lt;div class=&#34;gallery-grid&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-beon-2&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-2/artist.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Dr. Pacheco poses with her masterpiece: the symposium poster.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-2/artist_hua7cd33e8029c675120884ed44d2090b8_277339_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Dr. Pacheco poses with her masterpiece: the symposium poster.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-beon-2&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-2/coffee.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Coffee break offered an opportunity to mingle and continue the conversation.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-2/coffee_hu8107db2af1bc3b8d3014803687f48c29_266368_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Coffee break offered an opportunity to mingle and continue the conversation.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-beon-2&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-2/panel1.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Our first panel featured the speakers in an animated conversation with parallels in other regions, e.g., as Kenya.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-2/panel1_huec3c7036545790d12fb873ea77b9a15b_133445_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Our first panel featured the speakers in an animated conversation with parallels in other regions, e.g., as Kenya.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;341&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first panel featured a discussion on how to change social dynamics toward sustainability. This panel was a highlight of the symposium because regional experts are close to the communities on the ground at the forefront of conservation, connecting the global climate system, biodiversity threats, and sustainable solutions. Certification for Brazil nuts, for example, can promote that market over alternatives that produce more deforestation. But in some cases, as in Ecuador, enforcing laws already in the books can go a long way to mitigating climate change. Sometimes, events demonstrate why cultivating on steep land causes landslides, as in one of the municipalities Dr. Iñamagua studied, and this leads to mitigation. In other cases, as in Dr. Selaya’s work, infrastructure plays a larger role. Ultimately, Amazonians can only act on what they know, and channels such as Dr. Ribeiro’s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@EcoConexao/videos&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Eco-Conexão&lt;/a&gt; are vehicles for that transformation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

















&lt;div class=&#34;gallery-grid&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-beon-3&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-3/alencar.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Dr. Alencar asked how vulnerable are Amazon protected areas in Brazil?&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-3/alencar_hu5106ea7870f8ab5f7d9b07695a815b3f_199752_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Dr. Alencar asked how vulnerable are Amazon protected areas in Brazil?&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-beon-3&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-3/davalos.jpeg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Dr. Dávalos showed how criminal control shapes options for Amazon forests.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-3/davalos_hufb1ab47a7f7f19c5e2d33ad3806c0b09_345415_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Dr. Dávalos showed how criminal control shapes options for Amazon forests.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-beon-3&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-3/pacheco.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Dr. Pacheco presents options for forest restoration in Brazil&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-3/pacheco_hu8dbbbaaf91c0ae340df2ad9cd9916c7b_1949829_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Dr. Pacheco presents options for forest restoration in Brazil&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;422&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ipam.org.br/post_diretoria/ane-alencar-2/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Ane Alencar&lt;/a&gt; opened the second half of the symposium with her geospatial work on the vulnerability of Amazon protected areas in Brazil. Although only about 18% of the Amazon has been deforested so far, there is a real risk that nonlinear dynamics lead to a dreaded ‘tipping point,’ or the collapse of the forest ecosystem in favor of savanna. To avert this outcome, Brazil has designated a network of &amp;gt;6K Indigenous territories and protected areas covering almost half the basin. Nevertheless, some protected areas in Rio Negro and in Pará, along with the Yanomami Indigenous territory are under siege by land grabbing and illegal mining, among other causes of deforestation. With climate change extending the dry season by a week, triggering unprecedented droughts, fires have increased in Indigenous territories and many public lands. Still, Alencar’s work shows that land cover change places Brazil among the top 10 CO2 emitters, policy to enforce regulations has a real impact on curbing deforestation, and therefore there is a key opportunity to conserve Amazonian forests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, &lt;a href=&#34;https://research-information.bris.ac.uk/en/persons/rayane-pacheco-costa&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Rayane Pacheco&lt;/a&gt; shared her geospatial analyses on options for allocating forest restoration in the Brazilian Amazon. Through the Paris Climate Accord and national legislation, Brazil must restore 12 million hectares of degraded land by 2030. Pacheco created a pipeline to automate the selection of restoration sites on private properties in Pará that enables landholders, policymakers, and conservationists to optimize environmental and economic outcomes—such as enhancing connectivity and minimizing costs—while meeting legal requirements. Her pipeline is an essential and replicable tool for scaling restoration efforts to balance regional restoration goals with local implementation needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To close out the session, &lt;a href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/author/liliana-m.-davalos/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof. Liliana M. Dávalos&lt;/a&gt; presented her work on criminal networks in the Amazon. While several NGOs have highlighted the role of crime in deforestation in the region, Dávalos was skeptical because an explicitly quantitative link from illegal activities to forest loss was lacking. She showed traces of cocaine in European sewage have risen 17%/year for more than a decade, proving rising demand. Across the Atlantic in the Brazilian Amazon, seizures on this drug increased 47%/year for a few years, similar to taxes collected on gold in the same region. While trafficking skyrocketed in Brazil, coca production in Peru grew and shifted toward the border, and with it, forest loss across departments at the Brazilian border. Her work traces the illegal trafficking economy from consumers through traffickers along the Solimões Route, to burgeoning deforestation in Peru and thus connecting global illicit economies to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

















&lt;div class=&#34;gallery-grid&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-beon-4&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-4/lirr.JPEG&#34; data-caption=&#34;Fulbright is all about exchange and culture, here the climate change team experiences the Long Island Rairoad.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-4/lirr_hu70d86398f65dd7948ba0604c0a6fd92f_241924_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Fulbright is all about exchange and culture, here the climate change team experiences the Long Island Rairoad.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-beon-4&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-4/panel2.jpeg&#34; data-caption=&#34;The second panel attracted a spirited conversation about governance in the Amazon.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-4/panel2_hua4f1c4bc9ade9788000cd28521e9b112_597539_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;The second panel attracted a spirited conversation about governance in the Amazon.&#34; width=&#34;563&#34; height=&#34;750&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-beon-4&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-4/union.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;We made it to Union Station, Washington D.C.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/beon-4/union_hubdb00600ba0e2c2088e168fdc7f9d5ca_1960457_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;We made it to Union Station, Washington D.C.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the second panel and symposium closing, we discussed how recent political changes in the Amazon have shaped land use, land tenure, and illegal activity. While Dr. Alencar’s work shows the vast scale of Brazilian protected areas, it also shows threats are still active. Options for regrowth informed by spatial analyses, as in Dr. Pacheco’s work shows the importance of science in supporting policy and action. How to break up the criminal networks in the Amazon presented by Dr. Dávalos? Transnational cooperation to counter this web is beginning and will need to scale up. Thought-provoking questions from attendees made the symposium truly engaging!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the weekend after the symposium, the Fulbright Amazonia climate change team headed to Washington, D.C. by rail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;by-the-climate-change-fulbright-amazonia-scholars-ariek-norford-and-sayonthoni-das-tuhi&#34;&gt;By the Climate Change Fulbright Amazonia Scholars, Ariek Norford, and Sayonthoni Das Tuhi&lt;/h3&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gene Expression Shifts as Shrews Shrink and Regrow Their Brains</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/24-11-20-comparative-gene-expression/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/24-11-20-comparative-gene-expression/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.the-scientist.com/gene-expression-shifts-as-shrews-shrink-and-regrow-their-brains-72364&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Scientist&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://bsky.app/profile/hannahthomasy.bsky.social&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hannah Thomasy&lt;/a&gt; provides context for the new &lt;a href=&#34;https://elifesciences.org/reviewed-preprints/100788&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;reviewed preprint&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;../../author/william-r.-thomas/&#34;&gt;Bill Thomas&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;eLife&lt;/em&gt;. Congratulations, Bill! For more details, read the &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.stonybrook.edu/newsroom/press-release/general/study-uncovers-molecular-mechanisms-during-shrews-brain-changes/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stony Brook University news&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seasonal and comparative evidence of adaptive gene expression in mammalian brain size plasticity</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_seasonal_comparative_evidence_adaptive_gene_expression/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_seasonal_comparative_evidence_adaptive_gene_expression/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate Change in the Amazon Symposium</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/24-09-19-fulbright-amazonia-symposium/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/24-09-19-fulbright-amazonia-symposium/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our symposium on Climate Change in the Amazon took place from 12:30-5 pm on &lt;strong&gt;December 6, 2024&lt;/strong&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://iacs.stonybrook.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IACS&lt;/a&gt; Conference Room. This symposium brings together six Fulbright Amazonia scholars whose work spans disciplines in human and economic geography, policy, and remote sensing, all focused on climate change mitigation and adaptation in the Amazon. The symposium includes an Ask-Me-Anything lunch for students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;explore-more-about-the-fulbright-amazonia-projecthttpsfulbrightorgbrspecial-projectfulbright-amazonia-initiative-2022-2024&#34;&gt;Explore more about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://fulbright.org.br/special-project/fulbright-amazonia-initiative-2022-2024/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fulbright Amazonia project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This Amazon-themed symposium will provide the SBU community with opportunities to engage with  Fulbright Amazonia scholar during an Ask-Me-Anything (AMA) lunch and lab visits. At the AMA, students will hear about each Fulbright Amazonia scholar’s unique career trajectory both inside and outside academia. Such experiences provide a key opportunity to engage with undergraduate students who seek to make a difference through research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;meet-the-fulbright-amazonia-scholars&#34;&gt;Meet the Fulbright Amazonia Scholars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are an integrative science team. Learn more about our areas of expertise and research interests!&lt;/p&gt;

















&lt;div class=&#34;gallery-grid&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-geek-1&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/geek-1/AneAlencar.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Ane Alencar is the Science Director at Instituto de Pesquisa Ambiental da Amazonia (IPAM), a research based environmental Brazilian NGO that promotes sustainability, healthier environment and social justice in the Amazon. She graduated in Geography from the Federal University of Pará and holds a Master’s degree in Remote Sensing and Geographic Information Systems from Boston University, and a Ph.D. in Forest Resources and Conservation from the University of Florida. For the past three decades, she has been working at IPAM with the dynamics of deforestation, fire and forest degradation in relation to land use and climate change in the Amazon. She coordinates MapBiomas Fire, a comprehensive Brazil burned area monitoring initiative, as well as the Brazil Land Use Change Sector GHG estimate team of the Greenhouse Gas Emissions Estimation System (SEEG) initiative. She is one of the lead authors for the Scientific Panel for the Amazon and was recently listed as one of 14 female world leaders in the field of Machine Learning and Earth Observation by the Radiant Earth Foundation. As a Fulbright Amazonia Scholar, she will have the opportunity to integrate the knowledge of forest degradation by fire with other Pan Amazon countries in order to identify policy opportunities to reduce the impacts on Amazonian forest ecosystems.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/geek-1/AneAlencar_hu2fc9744d31952aadc529117ea86c5f09_890591_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Ane Alencar is the Science Director at Instituto de Pesquisa Ambiental da Amazonia (IPAM), a research based environmental Brazilian NGO that promotes sustainability, healthier environment and social justice in the Amazon. She graduated in Geography from the Federal University of Pará and holds a Master’s degree in Remote Sensing and Geographic Information Systems from Boston University, and a Ph.D. in Forest Resources and Conservation from the University of Florida. For the past three decades, she has been working at IPAM with the dynamics of deforestation, fire and forest degradation in relation to land use and climate change in the Amazon. She coordinates MapBiomas Fire, a comprehensive Brazil burned area monitoring initiative, as well as the Brazil Land Use Change Sector GHG estimate team of the Greenhouse Gas Emissions Estimation System (SEEG) initiative. She is one of the lead authors for the Scientific Panel for the Amazon and was recently listed as one of 14 female world leaders in the field of Machine Learning and Earth Observation by the Radiant Earth Foundation. As a Fulbright Amazonia Scholar, she will have the opportunity to integrate the knowledge of forest degradation by fire with other Pan Amazon countries in order to identify policy opportunities to reduce the impacts on Amazonian forest ecosystems.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;750&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-geek-1&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/geek-1/Davalos.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Liliana M. Dávalos is Professor of Conservation Biology at Stony Brook University (New York). Her research explores how biodiversity changes in time and space, what biological processes fuel biodiversity, and what are the social factors of environmental degradation. Dávalos is a 2012 National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine Education Fellow in the Life Sciences and a 2013 Kavli Frontiers of Science Fellow for outstanding early career. She has advised the United Nations Office of Drug and Crime (UNODC) on deforestation in the Amazon-Andes since 2007, and is the author or coauthor of over 100 peer-reviewed journal articles, a coauthor of the 2016 and 2022 UNODC World Drug Reports and a co-editor of two volumes on zoology and environmental science, most recently, Phyllostomid Bats: A Unique Mammalian Radiation (University of Chicago Press, 2020). She serves as director of awards for the Society for Systematic Biologists, Associate Editor for the Society’s flagship journal, Systematic Biology, and Editor in Chief for the Quarterly Review of Biology. For her Fulbright Amazonia research, Dávalos aims to discover how coca production and, especially, drug trafficking contribute to deforestation and land-grabbing dynamics across the western Amazon. Through this work, she hopes to illuminate and help anticipate narco-trafficking as a cross-border, multi-scale market that contributes to environmental degradation and undermines human communities across the region.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/geek-1/Davalos_hu1dfc857a158db9f67e2eeb7543e65901_1179407_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Liliana M. Dávalos is Professor of Conservation Biology at Stony Brook University (New York). Her research explores how biodiversity changes in time and space, what biological processes fuel biodiversity, and what are the social factors of environmental degradation. Dávalos is a 2012 National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine Education Fellow in the Life Sciences and a 2013 Kavli Frontiers of Science Fellow for outstanding early career. She has advised the United Nations Office of Drug and Crime (UNODC) on deforestation in the Amazon-Andes since 2007, and is the author or coauthor of over 100 peer-reviewed journal articles, a coauthor of the 2016 and 2022 UNODC World Drug Reports and a co-editor of two volumes on zoology and environmental science, most recently, Phyllostomid Bats: A Unique Mammalian Radiation (University of Chicago Press, 2020). She serves as director of awards for the Society for Systematic Biologists, Associate Editor for the Society’s flagship journal, Systematic Biology, and Editor in Chief for the Quarterly Review of Biology. For her Fulbright Amazonia research, Dávalos aims to discover how coca production and, especially, drug trafficking contribute to deforestation and land-grabbing dynamics across the western Amazon. Through this work, she hopes to illuminate and help anticipate narco-trafficking as a cross-border, multi-scale market that contributes to environmental degradation and undermines human communities across the region.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;750&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-geek-1&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/geek-1/I%C3%B1amagua.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Juan Pablo Iñamagua is a Lecturer at Ecuador’s Universidad de Cuenca, where he works with silvopastoral options for climate change mitigation and connectivity in livestock landscapes. His research focus is on understanding how agricultural landscapes contribute to ecosystem services provision, mainly to biodiversity and carbon sequestration. For this, he uses a participatory approach to identify native tree species of interest and later studies its ecology with the aim of including them in silvopastoral arrangements. He also studies the role of agricultural landscapes on wildlife presence. In his master and doctoral studies, he assessed direct greenhouse gas emissions on dairy farms in Costa Rica and the role of trees in livestock landscapes in the Coastal and Amazon region in Ecuador to account for farm negative emissions. His Fulbright Amazonia research will focus on silvopastoral options for climate change mitigation and how to improve the connectivity between livestock landscapes in the South of Ecuador’s Amazon region. The project aims to map and identify existing silvopastoral practices in the region, and to understand how local governments could support the adoption of these practices through local policies. The project will include different stakeholders and will explore their willingness to adopt silvopastoral practices, by communicating the possible impacts on climate change mitigation and connectivity.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/geek-1/I%C3%B1amagua_huc59b57cb8df371b063ce77f922bba1a8_1156524_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Juan Pablo Iñamagua is a Lecturer at Ecuador’s Universidad de Cuenca, where he works with silvopastoral options for climate change mitigation and connectivity in livestock landscapes. His research focus is on understanding how agricultural landscapes contribute to ecosystem services provision, mainly to biodiversity and carbon sequestration. For this, he uses a participatory approach to identify native tree species of interest and later studies its ecology with the aim of including them in silvopastoral arrangements. He also studies the role of agricultural landscapes on wildlife presence. In his master and doctoral studies, he assessed direct greenhouse gas emissions on dairy farms in Costa Rica and the role of trees in livestock landscapes in the Coastal and Amazon region in Ecuador to account for farm negative emissions. His Fulbright Amazonia research will focus on silvopastoral options for climate change mitigation and how to improve the connectivity between livestock landscapes in the South of Ecuador’s Amazon region. The project aims to map and identify existing silvopastoral practices in the region, and to understand how local governments could support the adoption of these practices through local policies. The project will include different stakeholders and will explore their willingness to adopt silvopastoral practices, by communicating the possible impacts on climate change mitigation and connectivity.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;750&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-geek-1&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/geek-1/Pacheco.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Rayane Pacheco is an Associate Researcher at Centro de Inteligência Territorial (CIT), working with spatial data analysis for conservation law enforcement on rural properties. She is an environmental researcher and geospatial data scientist, with an undergraduate degree in environmental management from the Federal Institute of Education, Science and Technology of Pará (IFPA), a master’s degree in environmental systems analysis and modeling and a doctorate in production engineering from the Federal University of Minas Gerais (UFMG). Pacheco has been working in the frontier of science and technology for the implementation of public policies in the Brazilian Amazon, in particular the Forest Code, the main forest conservation law in Brazil. Currently, she leads the development of methodological approaches for the territorial intelligence tool (CAR 2.0) that automatically assesses the Rural Environmental Registry (CAR) in the states of Pará and Minas Gerais, Brazil, an initiative of CIT in partnership with UFMG. Her Fulbright Amazonia research focuses on the spatial allocation of land for forest restoration to meet forest code requirements on private properties in the Brazilian Amazon.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/geek-1/Pacheco_hu4be74dd9b45cf68f7ebccdd9a36f4f96_876427_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Rayane Pacheco is an Associate Researcher at Centro de Inteligência Territorial (CIT), working with spatial data analysis for conservation law enforcement on rural properties. She is an environmental researcher and geospatial data scientist, with an undergraduate degree in environmental management from the Federal Institute of Education, Science and Technology of Pará (IFPA), a master’s degree in environmental systems analysis and modeling and a doctorate in production engineering from the Federal University of Minas Gerais (UFMG). Pacheco has been working in the frontier of science and technology for the implementation of public policies in the Brazilian Amazon, in particular the Forest Code, the main forest conservation law in Brazil. Currently, she leads the development of methodological approaches for the territorial intelligence tool (CAR 2.0) that automatically assesses the Rural Environmental Registry (CAR) in the states of Pará and Minas Gerais, Brazil, an initiative of CIT in partnership with UFMG. Her Fulbright Amazonia research focuses on the spatial allocation of land for forest restoration to meet forest code requirements on private properties in the Brazilian Amazon.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;750&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-geek-1&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/geek-1/Ribeiro.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Sabina Ribeiro is an associate professor at the Federal University of Acre. She graduated from the University of Brasília (UnB) and holds a Master’s and Doctorate in Forest management from Federal University of Viçosa (UFV). Her research has focused on the quantification of forest biomass and carbon stocks in the Atlantic forest, Cerrado (savannah) and Amazonia. She has also done applied research related to public policies concerning climate change. Ribeiro was PI on a 5-year NSF/USAID PEER “Forest Health Project” that included capacity building with extractive communities in Acre. Currently, Ribeiro is conducting research on forest dynamics in mature and secondary forests under the Prodigy project / Forest health consortium. She also leads the environmental work group of a project approved under the Amazonia&amp;#43;10 Initiative. Ribeiro’s Fulbright Amazonia project aims to disseminate scientific knowledge about climate change causes, adaptation and mitigation to traditional communities, mainly extractivists, as a way to foster sustainable development and reduce social inequalities in the state of Acre.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/geek-1/Ribeiro_hu4f015f996e7b67bdcb1aa533cb0c8303_295051_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Sabina Ribeiro is an associate professor at the Federal University of Acre. She graduated from the University of Brasília (UnB) and holds a Master’s and Doctorate in Forest management from Federal University of Viçosa (UFV). Her research has focused on the quantification of forest biomass and carbon stocks in the Atlantic forest, Cerrado (savannah) and Amazonia. She has also done applied research related to public policies concerning climate change. Ribeiro was PI on a 5-year NSF/USAID PEER “Forest Health Project” that included capacity building with extractive communities in Acre. Currently, Ribeiro is conducting research on forest dynamics in mature and secondary forests under the Prodigy project / Forest health consortium. She also leads the environmental work group of a project approved under the Amazonia&amp;#43;10 Initiative. Ribeiro’s Fulbright Amazonia project aims to disseminate scientific knowledge about climate change causes, adaptation and mitigation to traditional communities, mainly extractivists, as a way to foster sustainable development and reduce social inequalities in the state of Acre.&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;480&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-geek-1&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/geek-1/Selaya.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Galia Selaya is a Bolivian scientist with a Ph.D. in plant ecology and biodiversity. She is a researcher at the Forest Health Consortium-PRODIGY-BMBF project working with approaches to climate change in southwestern Amazonia through the lens of the theory of change. She focuses on anthropogenic drivers, wildfires, and climate change impacts on forests’ health and biodiversity functions in the tri-national region at the border of Bolivia (Pando), Peru (Madre de Dios), and Brazil (Acre). Previously, as a postdoc at the University of Florida, National Science Foundation project, she studied the synergetic dual economic and ecosystem services roles of species such as the Brazil nut tree (Bertholletia excelsa). Selaya conducts a multitemporal and multifactorial vegetation analysis from a network of permanent plots and remote sensing imagery. She works collaboratively with members of indigenous communities, forest dwellers, and stakeholders to monitor changes in forest carbon, productivity, and species resilience traits. She bridges participatory action research, scientific evidence, and citizen science for a diversified low-carbon emission economy and forest governance to address the anthropogenic and climate change threats to the Amazonian socio-ecological system. Her publication portfolio includes articles in ecology, society, and sustainability journals and multimedia outreach products for forest management and conservation.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/geek-1/Selaya_huf2a19e3db4f46849f12833530f1ce62b_472244_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Galia Selaya is a Bolivian scientist with a Ph.D. in plant ecology and biodiversity. She is a researcher at the Forest Health Consortium-PRODIGY-BMBF project working with approaches to climate change in southwestern Amazonia through the lens of the theory of change. She focuses on anthropogenic drivers, wildfires, and climate change impacts on forests’ health and biodiversity functions in the tri-national region at the border of Bolivia (Pando), Peru (Madre de Dios), and Brazil (Acre). Previously, as a postdoc at the University of Florida, National Science Foundation project, she studied the synergetic dual economic and ecosystem services roles of species such as the Brazil nut tree (Bertholletia excelsa). Selaya conducts a multitemporal and multifactorial vegetation analysis from a network of permanent plots and remote sensing imagery. She works collaboratively with members of indigenous communities, forest dwellers, and stakeholders to monitor changes in forest carbon, productivity, and species resilience traits. She bridges participatory action research, scientific evidence, and citizen science for a diversified low-carbon emission economy and forest governance to address the anthropogenic and climate change threats to the Amazonian socio-ecological system. Her publication portfolio includes articles in ecology, society, and sustainability journals and multimedia outreach products for forest management and conservation.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;750&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;schedule&#34;&gt;Schedule&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Time&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Speaker&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Topic&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12:30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fulbright Amazonia scholars &amp;amp; students&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;AMA: Designing and completing an interdisciplinary project: Climate-related disasters in the Amazon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13:00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fulbright Amazonia scholars &amp;amp; students&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Pizza Lunch&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13:55&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Lynch&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Opening remarks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14:00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Ribeiro&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dissemination of scientific knowledge about climate change for extractivist communities in Acre, Brazil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14:20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Iñamagua&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Mitigating climate change through productive landscape design&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14:40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Selaya&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Forest health at the Bolivia-Peru-Brazil triple border&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15:00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Interactive panel: Q&amp;amp;A with speakers&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15:15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Coffee Break&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15:30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Alencar&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;How vulnerable are Amazon protected areas?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15:50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Costa&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Options for forest restoration in Brazil&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16:00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dávalos&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Risks from criminal governance in the Amazon&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16:30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Interactive panel: Q&amp;amp;A with speakers&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16:45&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Closing&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cali lives up to CoP16, CBD fails to deliver money deal</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/24-10-28-davalos-at-cop16-cbd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/24-10-28-davalos-at-cop16-cbd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Will biodiversity make it? Out and about at the 16th Conference of the Parties to the Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD), read the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stonybrook.edu/commcms/igs/about/news_achievements.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;write-up&lt;/a&gt; at the Institute for Globalization Studies news. Or below the fold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, I returned from the 16th Conference of the Parties (or CoP) to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cbd.int/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Convention on Biological Diversity&lt;/a&gt; (CBD) in Cali, Colombia. This takes a bit of unpacking. Back in 1992, the United Nations sponsored the first CBD as a mechanism to halt the current extinction wave, the one our juggernaut of a human economy is causing, even as I write. Since then, pretty much &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cbd.int/information/parties.shtml&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;every country in the world&lt;/a&gt; has signed and ratified the CBD, though the United States signed then did not ratify it. In any case, the CBD has kept chugging along meeting every two years to reach consensus on agreements then actions to halt and even reverse the extinction wave. As a scientist working on biodiversity in tropical countries, in 2022, I had the privilege of working with a large team to provide &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cbd.int/doc/c/5735/c241/efeeac8d7685af2f38d75e4e/sbstta-24-inf-31-en.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;expert input&lt;/a&gt; so that the agreed-upon targets had a chance of &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.oneear.2022.05.009&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;curbing global extinctions&lt;/a&gt;. Because our team represented no single country, or party, to the Convention, this is analogous to the way expert testimony could be used in Congress here in the US. Ambitious targets were set to conserve life (animals! Plants! Fungi! Entire ecosystems!) on land and sea and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cbd.int/gbf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Global Biodiversity Framework&lt;/a&gt; was thus adopted in a very windy and frozen Montreal two years ago.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-dávalos-and-the-argentinian-surrealist-writer-julio-cortázar-at-café-valparaíso-cali-colombia&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./images/cortazar.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Dávalos, and the Argentinian surrealist writer Julio Cortázar at Café Valparaíso, Cali, Colombia.&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      Dávalos, and the Argentinian surrealist writer Julio Cortázar at Café Valparaíso, Cali, Colombia.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That set in motion the chain of events that took me to the decidedly less Arctic Cali, Colombia, in a totally unexpected manner. Back in Montreal, the parties decided to make good on their ambitious goals and implement (read: fund) them the next time, in Turkey. But 2023 earthquakes prevented Turkey from following, and for almost half of 2023, neither the parties nor the scientists and activists knew where CoP16 would be. Enter Colombia, a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.worldatlas.com/articles/ecologically-megadiverse-countries-of-the-world.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;megadiverse country&lt;/a&gt; hosting multiple distinct biodiversity hotspots, a state-backed national goal of becoming a biodiversity superpower, and in possession of Susana Muhamad, a minister of the environment with a long track record of environmental activism. Cali was selected at the international equivalent of the last minute, just last February and so had much less time to prepare than customary. Could scrappy Colombia and its Caleños (people from Cali) pull off such an undertaking?&lt;/p&gt;

















&lt;div class=&#34;gallery-grid&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-cop16-1&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-1/airport_host.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;At the Bogotá airport: Colombia, host of CoP16.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-1/airport_host_hu32db16f4c85955c671c3e142da1ffe4f_231416_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;At the Bogotá airport: Colombia, host of CoP16.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-cop16-1&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-1/peace_with_nature.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;At the Cali airport: the slogan of CoP16: Peace with Nature.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-1/peace_with_nature_huf844f5a8c03c8a051b770d58fd486111_209949_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;At the Cali airport: the slogan of CoP16: Peace with Nature.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reader, they did it! Even at airports, banners and exhibits proclaimed the importance of biodiversity everywhere. For CoP16, Cali itself was transformed. Streets, manhole covers, vents, everything highlighted biodiversity, until the Convention became inescapable. This may seem ineffectual, but I suspect it has brought biodiversity to the streets as never before. Take the multicolored tanager, &lt;em&gt;Chlorochryssa nitidissima&lt;/em&gt;, a bird that lives only on the Pacific versant of the Western Cordillera of Colombia, by most accounts the wettest rainforests in the world. As an undergraduate student, I went to the remote Munchique National Park and saw it as clouds rising from the Pacific Ocean briefly cleared. This memory is an inspiration to continue working to prevent the destruction of its forest home, no matter the odds. Yet, my deeply felt sense of the sublime will do nothing to stave off its demise, only action by people on the ground will and we can only save what we know. Over two short weeks, this one sign above a car park on Cali’s 4th Avenue reached more eyes and minds than my decades of presentations and publications!&lt;/p&gt;

















&lt;div class=&#34;gallery-grid&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-cop16-2&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-2/biodiversity_needs_solutions.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Out and about in Cali: biodiversity needs immediate solutions along the Avenida del Río.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-2/biodiversity_needs_solutions_hu4d7302bfc602e8197d3166b0a061df01_53871_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Out and about in Cali: biodiversity needs immediate solutions along the Avenida del Río.&#34; width=&#34;443&#34; height=&#34;293&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-cop16-2&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-2/manhole.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Manhole cover featuring the logo of CoP16, the Inírida flower found only in the Colombian rivers Guainía and Inírida.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-2/manhole_hu913304bbb1169c011d23c37b53a76d32_188552_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Manhole cover featuring the logo of CoP16, the Inírida flower found only in the Colombian rivers Guainía and Inírida.&#34; width=&#34;731&#34; height=&#34;684&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-cop16-2&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-2/tanager.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Out and about in Cali: picture of the multicolored tanager, &amp;lt;em&amp;gt;Chlorochryssa nitidissima&amp;lt;/em&amp;gt;, above a car park.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-2/tanager_hu50b5bab434b05225f0da51caa5cc984a_103066_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Out and about in Cali: picture of the multicolored tanager, *Chlorochryssa nitidissima*, above a car park.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;408&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But banners and slogans don’t generate change, people do, and this CoP was a record for public participation. The Green Zone, the area of the CoP open to the public, was like a block party along the Cali River, but for biodiversity. Expected to attract about 150,000 visitors during the 12 days of the Convention, as many arrived in just three days. All of Cali was packed, with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2024/oct/29/some-unique-features-cop16-delegates-in-love-motel-as-cali-hotels-hit-capacity&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;hotel occupancy&lt;/a&gt; at record rates and delegates packed both in Cali and towns surrounding it. Logistics were impeccable. Buses from the city’s service, were repurposed to connect the Green Zone with the secure area, or Blue Zone. One of the lines was all electric, and this new system outlives the Convention already, jumpstarting the transition to clean energy for local transport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But not all was fun and dance in the CoP Green Zone; stands reminded everyone nature is at stake! For example, an environmental assessment of the freshwater fish &lt;em&gt;Priapichthys caliensis&lt;/em&gt; found individuals only along 25-m of one of the Cali River’s tributaries. This is only known thanks to a small local NGO called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/people/Fundaci%C3%B3n-Funindes/100075623328871/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Funindes&lt;/a&gt;, which has a backlog of many other species to monitor. There were sobering exhibits. For example, the cemetery of recently extinct species showed species lost to the world as recently as the 2000s, in places as disparate as the Hawaiian archipelago, Tasmania, Costa Rica, or the Galapagos. But not all is lost, the garden of second chances features the many species that have been rescued from the brink of extinction by conservation action, including the iconic American bald eagle, or the Iberian lynx.&lt;/p&gt;

















&lt;div class=&#34;gallery-grid&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-cop16-3&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-3/cali_fish.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Out and about in the Green Zone: endemic fish Priapichthys caliensis, known from a mere 25-yard stretch upstream from the Cali river.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-3/cali_fish_hu393e839b1cf5852061d7d36cc08811d3_126219_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Out and about in the Green Zone: endemic fish Priapichthys caliensis, known from a mere 25-yard stretch upstream from the Cali river.&#34; width=&#34;667&#34; height=&#34;460&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-cop16-3&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-3/extinct.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Out and about in the Green Zone: a cemetery of recently extinct species, some within the last 20 years.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-3/extinct_hu183fd16c6c56cacf88c3d5f0c459a5e0_414976_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Out and about in the Green Zone: a cemetery of recently extinct species, some within the last 20 years.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-cop16-3&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-3/party.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Out and about in the Green Zone: a giant block party along the Cali River.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-3/party_huf326992d0b3906ad43acf815c0a671d1_522306_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Out and about in the Green Zone: a giant block party along the Cali River.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-cop16-3&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-3/second_chances.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Out and about in the Green Zone: Garden of Second Chances, species saved by conservation action, such as the American bald eagle.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-3/second_chances_huc086674e9ad60bef33f116f2d24ea32b_369990_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Out and about in the Green Zone: Garden of Second Chances, species saved by conservation action, such as the American bald eagle.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-cop16-3&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-3/vents.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Out and about in the Green Zone: service vents along the river park also featured biodiversity, in the case the Andean bear.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-3/vents_hue411bae17127320a13bde6afcbfdff77_372062_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Out and about in the Green Zone: service vents along the river park also featured biodiversity, in the case the Andean bear.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own participation featured the rescue of just one such species, the Jamaican flower bat, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iucnredlist.org/species/17173/22133396&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Phyllonycteris aphylla&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Back in the 2000s, I joined expert panels determining the extinction threat status of many species of bats in Latin America and the Caribbean. As a publication featured dozens of locations for the Jamaican flower bat, I classified the species as not endangered at all. But I had overlooked the dates of those sightings, all were old, some as old as 30 or 50 years. An expert based out of Jamaica, Dr. Susan Koenig, pointed this out, adding that Andrea Donaldson from the National Environmental Planning Agency of Jamaica had found this species at just one cave in the whole country. Susan and I then worked together to recategorize this species, finding it was critically endangered. This enabled a NGO, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.batcon.org/home/bats-and-biodiversity/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bat Conservation International&lt;/a&gt;, to kick into gear and raise funds to save the species from extinction. Their prompt action and support from the Jamaican landowner who wanted to leave a legacy for future generations have made all the difference. Their BCI-Jamaica team now work together on excluding feral cats that threaten bat pups as well as restoring the habitat where these bats forage.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-how-bat-conservation-contributes-to-global-biodiversity-and-sustainable-development-goals-side-event-by-bat-conservation-international-picture-by-mylea-bayless&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./images/BCI_side_event.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;How Bat Conservation Contributes to Global Biodiversity and Sustainable Development Goals side event by Bat Conservation International. Picture by Mylea Bayless.&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
      How Bat Conservation Contributes to Global Biodiversity and Sustainable Development Goals side event by Bat Conservation International. Picture by Mylea Bayless.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Global events like the CoP can seem far removed from immediate threats to biodiversity, such as ecosystem loss and climate change. In the end, this round of negotiations succeeded in establishing the &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.mongabay.com/2024/10/cop16-a-fund-unlike-any-other-will-pay-tropical-nations-to-save-forests/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tropical Forest Forever Facility&lt;/a&gt; (or TFFF) by paying out dividends to conserve the world’s most biodiverse forests. It also established the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.forbes.com/sites/davidcarlin/2024/11/04/cop-16s-chaotic-end-what-it-means-for-the-future-of-biodiversity/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Cali Fund&lt;/a&gt;, to draw from large companies that make use of genetic resources in support of biodiversity. Most consequentially, Indigenous peoples now have their own seat at the negotiation table, a landmark decision. But there was no agreement on a mechanism to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2024/nov/03/cop16-ends-in-disarry-and-indecision-despite-biodiversity-breakthroughs&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;finance the annual $200 billion needed to avert extinctions&lt;/a&gt;, and the CoP ended as delegates vacated the room to take their flights. It was not the expected outcome, but watching so many come together for biodiversity, especially in the Green Zone, was invigorating. Let’s hope all this activism translates into action!&lt;/p&gt;

















&lt;div class=&#34;gallery-grid&#34;&gt;

  
  
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-cop16-0&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-0/no_more_fossils.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;They probably mean fossil fuels, but we get the point.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-0/no_more_fossils_hu04bc0b3ac007315743695af15723bec1_353959_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;They probably mean fossil fuels, but we get the point.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  
    
    
    
    
    
      
        
      
    
  
  
  &lt;div class=&#34;gallery-item gallery-item--medium&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;gallery-cop16-0&#34; href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-0/plant-based.jpeg&#34; data-caption=&#34;On the walk to register: Animal consumption is destroying biodiversity. Approve a plant-based diet. Picture by Mónica Medina.&#34;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/albums/cop16-0/plant-based_hu4e086219fd789e2b17a8c526520714b6_586913_750x750_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;On the walk to register: Animal consumption is destroying biodiversity. Approve a plant-based diet. Picture by Mónica Medina.&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;563&#34;&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From the Bat Cave – Integrative Disease Ecology Research for Undergraduates</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/24-09-18-batcave/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/24-09-18-batcave/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have extended our application deadline to &lt;strong&gt;November 15, 2024&lt;/strong&gt;. We are seeking self-motivated, curious, and collaborative students for an exciting 7-week paid National Science Foundation (NSF) research experience investigating environment-host-virome dynamics within wild Egyptian fruit bats (&lt;em&gt;Rousettus aegyptiacus&lt;/em&gt;). This interactive learning and research opportunity introduces undergraduates to integrative disease research, including fieldwork in Puerto Rico! Students will receive guided mentorship, attend daily group meetings, and get hands-on training in fieldwork, data analysis, coding, and science communication!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;become-a-member-of-the-bat-cave&#34;&gt;Become a member of the Bat Cave!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you ready to sink your teeth into cutting-edge research?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you have an interest in disease ecology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would you like to learn more about bats, ecology, and viromes?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are you looking for an opportunity to conduct field research?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;join-the-batcave-for-summer-2025-and-emerge-a-scientist&#34;&gt;Join the BatCave for Summer 2025 and emerge a scientist!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;batcaveimagesbatcavepng&#34;&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./images/batcave.png&#34; alt=&#34;batcave&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-the-project&#34;&gt;About the Project!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In nature, encounters between humans and wildlife correlate with greater viral burdens in wildlife and therefore with higher risk of new viral pathogens spilling over into human populations. Yet, the factors contributing to this risk remain poorly understood, especially among highly mobile, but tightly packed populations of animals, such as cave-dwelling bats. Using the Egyptian fruit bat as a study system, this project seeks to understand how factors such as access to food, overall animal health, and responses to immune challenges influence each other in the wild to control the degree of viral infection in populations experiencing variable exposure to humans. This project funded by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=2217296&amp;amp;HistoricalAwards=false&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;National Science Foundation (NSF)&lt;/a&gt;   applies highly integrative approaches to illuminate the fundamental biology of disease risk and to enhance the capacity to predict risks of viral spillover from bats to other wildlife or to humans. From the Bat Cave is an educational module for undergraduates that offers an interactive learning and research-based introduction to integrative disease research using  project data. Because Nigeria is a long way off, we introduce students to field ecology in Puerto Rico. Find out more about the course details and objectives below!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;grant-awards&#34;&gt;Grant Awards&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Collaborative Research: Integrated mechanisms of environment-host-virome interactions (2217295) to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=2217295&amp;amp;HistoricalAwards=false&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Texas Tech&lt;/a&gt;, (2217296) to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=2217296&amp;amp;HistoricalAwards=false&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SBU and VIDO/USask&lt;/a&gt;, and (2217297) to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=2217297&amp;amp;HistoricalAwards=false&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;UC-Davis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;../../project/integrated_mechanisms_environment_host_virome&#34;&gt;project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;course-details&#34;&gt;Course Details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🔬 What you&amp;rsquo;ll do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dive into real data from wild Egyptian fruit bats in Nigeria&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Master tools in ecology, genomics, and virology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work in diverse teams to tackle integrative research questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn to communicate science like a pro&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Participate in fieldwork in the forests of Puerto Rico!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🌟 Who we&amp;rsquo;re looking for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eligible participants must be US citizens, US nationals, or US permanent residents
Juniors, Seniors, or people who have graduated within the last year (May 2024) in biology or related fields at any US institution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Curious minds eager to learn across disciplines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Team players ready to collaborate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Undergraduates from all backgrounds - we especially encourage applications from underrepresented minorities in STEM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;💪 What you&amp;rsquo;ll gain:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hands-on research and field experience in disease ecology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Training in field techniques to study bats in their natural habitat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mentorship from expert scientists in ecology, genomics, and virology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skills in data analysis, coding, and scientific communication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A supportive peer network across three universities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preparation for graduate school or science careers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🏫 Where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Online program connecting students from across the US&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Field training in Puerto Rico&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📅 When:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May 19 - July 3, 2025&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Puerto Rico travel dates: June 11 - June 21, 2025&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Available in Spring 2025 for training, vaccination schedules, fit tests etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;💰 Compensation: Stipend for this full-time course of 7 weeks is $5,000. Travel to Puerto Rico is funded separately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t let this opportunity fly by! Apply now to join the Bat Cave and be part of groundbreaking research while exploring the fascinating world of bats!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Application deadline: &lt;strong&gt;November 15, 2024&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSchLEbcL2CDvgfwQTMjb09R1f0qXwkS6Pl7Ffi8ZfyyMt6uIg/viewform?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Apply here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;meet-the-teamteam&#34;&gt;Meet the &lt;a href=&#34;../../team&#34;&gt;Team&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./images/PR_team.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;PR_team&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are an integrative science team. &lt;a href=&#34;../../team&#34;&gt;Learn more about our areas of expertise and research interests!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meet the Team!</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/team/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/team/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovery and biological confirmation of a highly divergent Tacaribe virus in metatranscriptomic data from neotropical bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_discovery_biological_confirmation_highly_divergent_tacaribe_virus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_discovery_biological_confirmation_highly_divergent_tacaribe_virus/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human and bats genome robustness under COSMIC mutational signatures</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/preprint_human_bats_genome_robustness_cosmic_mutational/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2024 00:00:01 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/preprint_human_bats_genome_robustness_cosmic_mutational/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>People</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/people/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/people/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paul Donat graduates from his Ph.D.!</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/24-05-14-donat-hooding/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/24-05-14-donat-hooding/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../author/paul-donat&#34;&gt;Paul Donat&lt;/a&gt; graduated in the Spring 2024 doctoral hooding ceremony and continues his work as science teacher at Hampton Bays Public Schools. Dr. Donat&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;../publication/thesis_sex_chromosomes_evolution_models/&#34;&gt;dissertation&lt;/a&gt; explored new sex chromosomes in &lt;em&gt;Humulus&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Artibeus jamaicensis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparative Genomics in Clades Emerging as Sex Chromosome Evolution Models</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/thesis_sex_chromosomes_evolution_models/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/thesis_sex_chromosomes_evolution_models/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neotropics as a Cradle for Adaptive Radiations</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_neotropics_as_cradle_adaptive_radiations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_neotropics_as_cradle_adaptive_radiations/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolvability of cancer-associated genes under APOBEC3A/B selection</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_evolvability_cancer_associated_under_apobec3_selection/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_evolvability_cancer_associated_under_apobec3_selection/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frugivore traits predict plant-frugivore interactions using generalized joint attribute modeling</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_testing_reciprocal_plant_interactions_generalized_attribute/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_testing_reciprocal_plant_interactions_generalized_attribute/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lab in the News</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/lab_in_news/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/lab_in_news/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>People</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/alumni/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/alumni/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/contact/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cochlea development shapes bat sensory system evolution</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_cochlea_development_shapes_bat_sensory_system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_cochlea_development_shapes_bat_sensory_system/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>As Colombia’s coca economy crashes, new opportunities — and threats — arise</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-11-15-coca-economy-crashes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-11-15-coca-economy-crashes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This analysis by &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.mongabay.com/by/mie-hoejris-dahl/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mie Dahl&lt;/a&gt; includes several &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.mongabay.com/2023/11/as-colombias-coca-economy-crashes-new-opportunities-and-threats-arise/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;quotes by Dávalos&lt;/a&gt;. While minor compared to the deforestation caused by clearing for pasture, coca cultivation still affects local communities through contamination of soil and water, violence and crime — yet remains a vital source of livelihood for more than 230,000 families.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robust evidence for bats as reservoir hosts is lacking in most African virus studies: a review and call to optimize sampling and conserve bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_robust_evidence_bats_reservoirs_africa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_robust_evidence_bats_reservoirs_africa/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The evolution of antimicrobial peptides in Chiroptera</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_evolution_antimicrobial_peptides_chiroptera/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_evolution_antimicrobial_peptides_chiroptera/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bill defends his dissertation</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-09-14-thomas-defends-shrew-dissertation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-09-14-thomas-defends-shrew-dissertation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Doctoral candidate William Thomas is a candidate no more after successfully defending his &lt;a href=&#34;../publication/thesis_shrinking_shrews/&#34;&gt;dissertation&lt;/a&gt;! Congratulations to Dr. Thomas!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shrinking Shrews: Evolutionary history and molecular mechanisms of a unique wintering strategy</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/thesis_shrinking_shrews/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/thesis_shrinking_shrews/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BIO 336/BEE572: Conservation Biology</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/course/24-08-26-bio-336/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/course/24-08-26-bio-336/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To be taught Fall 2024. Active learning course. Introduces the scientific foundations of conservation biology, along with real-world examples. Seven learning units: demography, population genetics, between-species interactions, island biogeography, biogeochemistry, and environmental economics. Classroom is flipped, course includes pre- and post-assessments of class content, activities in every class period, numerous take-home exercises, online-based textbooks, and open-notes exams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course has been part of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=0942789&amp;amp;HistoricalAwards=false&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NSF-funded project&lt;/a&gt; to evaluate the effectiveness of one-semester interventions in building critical thinking skills. Results show that students do gain &lt;a href=&#34;https://online.ucpress.edu/cse/article/5/1/1536396/118929/Using-Case-Studies-to-Improve-the-Critical&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;some critical thinking skills&lt;/a&gt; as part of the course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Credits: 3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hours: 2 lectures (80-min each) per week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grading type: A-F&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instructor: &lt;a href=&#34;../about/&#34;&gt;Liliana M. Dávalos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GLI 320: Global, Cultural, and Environmental Issues</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/course/24-08-26-gli-320/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/course/24-08-26-gli-320/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To be taught Fall 2024. Provides a critical understanding of how environmental problems and conflicts have roots in global social processes (such as culture, community, and political and economic inequality), and how these social forces in turn bear on the ways individuals and groups understand environmental problems and politically mobilize to change them. Specific emphases of the course deal with the links, at a global scale, between environmental degradation and various social problems like violence, spreading of disease, and international migration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prerequisite: GLI 211&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DEC:     H&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SBC:     STAS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 credits&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instructor: &lt;a href=&#34;../about/&#34;&gt;Liliana M. Dávalos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evolutionary potential of the monkeypox genome arising from interactions with human APOBEC3 enzymes</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_evolutionary_potential_monkeypox_genome_human_apobec3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_evolutionary_potential_monkeypox_genome_human_apobec3/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nicolette Sipperly presents at Botany 2023</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-07-30-nicolette-at-botanical-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-07-30-nicolette-at-botanical-conference/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Doctoral candidate Nicolette Sipperly presented at &lt;a href=&#34;https://2023.botanyconference.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Botany Conference 2023&lt;/a&gt;. Nicolette showed results from her phenotypic comparisons across populations of Draba albertina, and connections between art and science. Congratulations to Nicolette!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Doctoral candidates present at Evolution 2023</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-06-25-students-present-evolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-06-25-students-present-evolution/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Doctoral candidates Alexis Brown and William Thomas presented at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.xcdsystem.com/evolution/program/URURiZb/index.cfm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Evolution 2023&lt;/a&gt;. While Lexi presented  &amp;ldquo;Evidence for novel molecular mechanisms for resisting sensorineural hearing loss in echolocating bats,&amp;rdquo; Bill presented &amp;ldquo;Comparative transcriptomics reveal life history tradeoffs associated with the evolution of a seasonal size plasticity in shrews.&amp;rdquo; Congratulations to both!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>War on drugs and Colombia&#39;s forests</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-06-24-silent-victims-war-drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-06-24-silent-victims-war-drugs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This analysis by &lt;a href=&#34;https://explorer-directory.nationalgeographic.org/gena-g-steffens&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Gena Steffens&lt;/a&gt; includes several &lt;a href=&#34;https://english.elpais.com/international/2023-06-24/colombias-forests-silent-victims-of-the-war-on-drugs.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;quotes by Dávalos&lt;/a&gt;. Informed by on-the-ground reporting from San José del Guaviare, Steffens highlights the failures of drug policy in the Amazon-Andes region.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Estimating the Impact of Narcotrafficking on Amazon Forest Conversion and Land Grabbing</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/fulbright_amazonia/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/fulbright_amazonia/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mongabay revisits predictions on Amazonian deforestation</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-05-19-million-hectares-colombian-amazon/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-05-19-million-hectares-colombian-amazon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Decades ago and writing using a pseudonym, Dávalos wondered &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1023/A:1012904318418&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;whether peace could be worse than war&lt;/a&gt;. In Mongabay, &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.mongabay.com/by/antonio-jose-paz-cardona/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Antonio Paz &lt;/a&gt; revisits this &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.mongabay.com/2023/05/3-million-hectares-of-colombian-amazon-deforested-for-illegal-pasture-study/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;question&lt;/a&gt;, highlighting new empirical insights that confirm the dire predictions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dávalos Earns First-Ever Fulbright Amazonia Fellowship</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-05-15-fulbright-amazonia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-05-15-fulbright-amazonia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A newly established Fulbright Scholar Program called &lt;a href=&#34;https://fulbrightprogram.org/fulbright-amazonia/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fulbright Amazonia&lt;/a&gt; supports an international network of scientists who will carry out research dedicated to protecting the diverse wildlife and indigenous communities of the Amazon. Dávalos will investigate the effect of coca cultivation and cocaine trafficking on &lt;a href=&#34;https://fulbrightscholars.org/amazonia#custom&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amazonian wildlife and communities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Histological and MRI brain atlas of the common shrew, Sorex araneus, with brain region-specific gene expression profiles</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_histological_mri_brain_atlas/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_histological_mri_brain_atlas/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Insights into mammalian TE diversity via the curation of 248 mammalian genome assemblies</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_insight_into_mammalian_tes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_insight_into_mammalian_tes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morphology and niche evolution influence hummingbird speciation rates</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_morphology_niche_evolution_influence_hummingbird_speciation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_morphology_niche_evolution_influence_hummingbird_speciation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chiropterans are a hotspot for horizontal transfer of DNA transposons in Mammalia</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_chiropterans_hotspot_horizontal_transfer_dna_transposons/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_chiropterans_hotspot_horizontal_transfer_dna_transposons/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disentangling mechanical and sensory modules in the radiation of Noctilionoid bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_disentangling_mechanical_sensory_modules_radiation_noctilionoid_bats/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_disentangling_mechanical_sensory_modules_radiation_noctilionoid_bats/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lab manager opportunity! No longer taking applications</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-04-06-hiring-lab-manager/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-04-06-hiring-lab-manager/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The job in brief&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;purpose&lt;/strong&gt; of this &lt;a href=&#34;https://stonybrooku.taleo.net/careersection/2/jobdetail.ftl?job=2300709&amp;amp;tz=GMT-05%3A00&amp;amp;tzname=America%2FNew_York&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;job&lt;/a&gt; is to oversee operations of our on-campus research laboratory focusing on biodiversity genomics at Stony Brook University, Stony Brook, New York. This is a lab manager position encompassing about 50% bench and 50% administrative lab support. While the position is currently funded for 5 years, I aim to renew it and it may become a permanent staff position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a &lt;strong&gt;salary&lt;/strong&gt; range of up to $55K salary with benefits, depending on qualifications. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.suny.edu/media/suny/content-assets/documents/benefits/benefit-summaries/FTUUPbenefitsummary-December-2022.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Benefits&lt;/a&gt; at Stony Brook University are excellent include vacation and paid sick leave, in addition to excellent health, dental, and vision insurance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your unique goals and skills can &lt;strong&gt;shape&lt;/strong&gt; this position. For example, depending on your career goals, the position can offer excellent insight into graduate education and long-term research careers. You can contribute to research publications.
We apply the &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23813053/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;authorship matrix&lt;/a&gt; approach to authorship, and lab management contributions count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My goal is to make this job an &lt;strong&gt;opportunity&lt;/strong&gt; to conduct key aspects of scientific research without having to constantly worry about funding, or completing a thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click on the title👆🏽for more under the fold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What will you be doing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You will:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oversee maintenance of the bench and computer lab functions. I will work with you to review this. In brief, it involves making sure we don&amp;rsquo;t run out of essential supplies and that various computers work and lab data are safe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relatedly, manage lab compliance and schedules. We work with animal samples brought from the field that fall under regulation by the University and the Federal Government.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manage expenses. Our lab is funded through multiple projects and fund types that follow different rules and timelines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manage and work in collaboration with a team of postdoctoral researchers, graduate students, and occasional visitors to the lab&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With support from the entire lab team, I have been conducting most of these tasks myself for 15 years. Although we have systems in place, I&amp;rsquo;m sure we can improve them with your creativity and drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the difference between this job and a research assistant (e.g., graduate student)?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unlike a research assistantship, this may become a permanent position. It will last at least 5 years with current funding, and we will seek to make it permanent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most research assistants are associated with individual projects, here you will work across projects and the focus is on keeping the lab humming, for a longer time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A (graduate) research assistant at Stony Brook State makes $37K plus benefits, and this job is up to $55K plus full-time employee benefits. I.e., the salary is higher.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is more flexibility in how we collaborate. Both undergraduate and graduate student research assistante are constantly working toward their graduation. Graduate students are expected to collect and analyze data, then write their findings. Although you may carve out a project of your own, how we collaborate and on what timeline is flexible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For these reasons, I expect the job will be less stressful and more conducive toward &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stonybrook.edu/commcms/jobs/working-here/index.php&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;work-life balance&lt;/a&gt;, while still participating and depending on interests, advancing, in scientific research.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What makes an outstanding applicant?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are passionate about scientific research.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are kind towards others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You uphold high ethical standards in your work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You are motivated to persevere and overcome obstacles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You bring a conscientious, organized, and detail-oriented approach to work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have some relevant experience (e.g., managing a project, or through internships).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can communicate clearly and effectively, including providing and taking honest feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can be adaptable and creative.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about past experience?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many different forms of past experience count. For example, a laboratory internship or project management of your own can count. Laboratory research assistantships also count, especially insofar as you have helped advance a own project. Advanced degrees are not required, but you won&amp;rsquo;t be overqualified with a master&amp;rsquo;s degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to apply&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Upload your CV and cover letter to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://stonybrooku.taleo.net/careersection/2/jobdetail.ftl?job=2300709&amp;amp;tz=GMT-05%3A00&amp;amp;tzname=America%2FNew_York&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;online system&lt;/a&gt;. Here is what to emphasize:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CV:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;your science degree,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;experience with data organization, project or lab management for any area of lab-based biology or environmental science,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;basic (or more advanced) bench and computer skills too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Letter:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are your scientific interests?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How have your past experience and background prepared you for this job?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What makes &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; an excellent candidate for this position?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are your career goals?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will this position support those career goals? (I.e., areas of growth)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There is a deadline&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Applications will close on May 19, 2023. Contact &lt;a href=&#34;https://lmdavalos.github.io/#contact&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;me&lt;/a&gt; with questions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Path to Climate Stability: Unleashing the Power of Azolla for Carbon Sequestration</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/azolla_carbon_capture/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/azolla_carbon_capture/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BEE 690: Ethics in Genetics and Genomics</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/course/23-01-22-bee-690/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/course/23-01-22-bee-690/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Taught Spring 2023. A seminar on ethics and genetics and genomics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>La fauna de Madagascar se enfrenta a una ola inminente de extinción</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-01-11-ola-extincion-inminente/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-01-11-ola-extincion-inminente/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;¡Aún hay tiempo para &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-022-35215-3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;salvar&lt;/a&gt; los mamíferos amenazados de Madagascar! Esta reseña en &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.muyinteresante.es/actualidad/59252.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Muy Interesante&lt;/a&gt; resalta los desafíos para la conservación.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The deep evolutionary impact of Madagascar’s imminent extinction wave</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-01-10-deep-evolutionary-impact/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/23-01-10-deep-evolutionary-impact/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What if the threatened mammals of Madagascar are effectively conserved? Millions of years of evolutionary history would be &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-022-35215-3&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;saved&lt;/a&gt;! Check out this write-up from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/d44148-023-00003-8&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nature&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/d44148-023-00003-8#author-0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Paul Adepoju&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The macroevolutionary impact of recent and imminent mammal extinctions on Madagascar</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_macroevolutionary_impact_mammal_extinctions_madagascar/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_macroevolutionary_impact_mammal_extinctions_madagascar/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roads and deforestation in the Colombian Amazon</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-12-13-deudas-ambientales-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-12-13-deudas-ambientales-2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s balance of deforestation in the Colombian Amazon? Check out this report at &lt;a href=&#34;https://es.mongabay.com/2022/12/deudas-ambientales-de-colombia-en-2022-asesinatos-de-lideres-deforestacion/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mongabay LatAm&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://es.mongabay.com/by/antonio-jose-paz-cardona/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Antonio Paz &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Actions needed to achieve ambitious objectives of net gains in natural ecosystem area by 2030 and beyond</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_actions_needed_to_achieve_ambitious/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_actions_needed_to_achieve_ambitious/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting ambitious international restoration objectives for terrestrial ecosystems for 2030 and beyond</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_setting_ambitious_international_restoration/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_setting_ambitious_international_restoration/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Military solutions to deforestation are flashy, but lack impact</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-12-05-artemisa-radiografia-operacion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-12-05-artemisa-radiografia-operacion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Did Operación Artemisa, a military effort to stop deforestation, work? Not according to  this report at &lt;a href=&#34;https://es.mongabay.com/2022/12/artemisa-radiografia-de-una-operacion-que-no-freno-la-deforestacion-en-colombia/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mongabay LatAm&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://es.mongabay.com/by/david-tarazona-y-julian-parra-de-moya/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;David Tarazona and Julian Parra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An end to conflict and expansion of deforestation</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-12-01-postconflicto-deforestacion/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-12-01-postconflicto-deforestacion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in 2001, during a temporary rapprochement, Liliana &lt;a href=&#34;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1023/A:1012904318418&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;predicted &lt;/a&gt; bursts of deforestation following the end of conflict. Decades later, the data bear this prediction out check out this synthesis at &lt;a href=&#34;https://es.mongabay.com/2022/12/un-posconflicto-marcado-por-la-deforestacion-en-colombia/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mongabay LatAm&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://es.mongabay.com/by/antonio-jose-paz-cardona/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Antonio Paz &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why this mammal eats its own brain</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-11-30-mammal-eats-own-brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-11-30-mammal-eats-own-brain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/people/dino-grandoni/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dino Grandoni&lt;/a&gt; has written an excellent perspective on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/climate-environment/2022/11/30/shrews-shrink-regrow-own-brains/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;shrew project&lt;/a&gt; for the Washington Post!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New postdoc opportunity!</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-09-23-new-postdoc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-09-23-new-postdoc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Together with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vido.org/team/project-leaders-veterinarians/angela-rasmussen&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Angela Rasmussen&lt;/a&gt;, were hiring an #integrative biology #postdoc! Love🦇 #bats, 🧬 #ecology, #evolution, #viruses 🦠? Come work with us on a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=2217296&amp;amp;HistoricalAwards=false&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NSF funded&lt;/a&gt; collaboration with Tigga Kingston and Simon Anthony. This position is now closed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Required Qualifications&lt;/strong&gt;:
Doctoral Degree (or foreign equivalent) in ecological virology, physiology, metabolism, and/or immunology, or closely related field in hand by January 2023. Proven interests in integrative science crossing disciplines and in mentoring students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preferred Qualifications&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br&gt;
Excellent communication skills across disciplines as demonstrated by peer-reviewed scientific manuscripts. Keen interest in or experience with high dimensional, integrative data analyses. Applicants should be willing to work as part of a diverse multidisciplinary and multicultural team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brief Description of Duties&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;br&gt;
Our goal is to discover the mechanisms governing relationships among the environment, the wildlife host, and the viral communities they support by answering three key questions: (1) how do host abundance, reproduction, age, and condition differentially or interactively influence viral diversity; (2) how does the host respond to stressors in wild populations; and (3) how do gene expression profiles and viral infection influence one another in the wild?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The postdoctoral researcher at Stony Brook and VIDO/USask will primarily focus on the second and third questions while working closely with two other postdoctoral researchers at collaborating institutions. Approaches to answering these questions will include transcriptomics, data integration, and some field work. As part of the project, the postdoctoral researcher will have ample opportunity to build on or acquire primary skill sets in RNA-seq analyses and secondary skill sets in fieldwork, viral discovery, training in biocontainment procedures, big data, and integrative analyses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The incumbent will conduct research in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stonybrook.edu/ecoevo/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Department of Ecology and Evolution&lt;/a&gt; and ensure that all experiments are appropriately conducted following the policies and procedures of Stony Brook University. For more information please visit the Davalos Lab website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duties&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collect and analyze transcriptomic genetic data, integrate with data sets collected by collaborators, and conduct some field work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build on or acquire primary skill sets in RNA-seq analyses and secondary skill sets in fieldwork, viral discovery, training in biocontainment procedures, and big data, integrative analyses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prepare manuscripts including writing, editing, and figure preparation. May also assist in grant writing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advance mentoring by helping develop and implement an innovative active-learning experience called “From the Bat Cave – Integrative Disease Research for Undergraduates.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work in close collaboration with two other postdoctoral researchers at TTU and UC Davis, as well as the four PIs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other duties as assigned, which may include attending Scientific Conferences and Meetings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dávalos talks genomics and the Amazon at United Nations General Assembly side event</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-09-16-davalos-amazon/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-09-16-davalos-amazon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alongside other experts from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theamazonwewant.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Science Panel for the Amazon&lt;/a&gt; and industry, PI Dávalos spoke at the United Nations General Assembly side event on &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/yL9Y-RsfgiY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The Amazon as a Bioeconomy Superpower: Investing in Innovation and Technology for Sustainable Development&lt;/a&gt; which highlighted sustainable options for regional economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A solution to the challenges of interdisciplinary aggregation and use of specimen-level trait data</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_challenges_interdisciplinary_aggregation_specimen_level/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_challenges_interdisciplinary_aggregation_specimen_level/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrated mechanisms of environment-host-virome interactions</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/integrated_mechanisms_environment_host_virome/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/integrated_mechanisms_environment_host_virome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Human disruption of the environment is thought to play a central role in disease emergence in wildlife populations by reducing the availability of foods and refuge that animals rely upon, thereby stressing the animals and making them more susceptible to viruses. However, the mechanisms governing relationships among the environment, the wildlife host, and the viral communities they support are poorly known. To address this problem, the project will take advantage of a single cohesive wild system of Egyptian fruit bats (Rousettus aegyptiacus) to sample animals of different sex, age, and reproductive condition from caves that support different numbers of bats, are subject to variable levels of hunting, and are surrounded by different qualities of foraging habitat and hence food resources. Using each individual bat as the unit of observation, analyses will aim to relate landscape resources, and individual condition and immunity to viral profiles, thus answering three key questions: (1) how do host abundance, reproduction, age, and condition differentially or interactively influence viral diversity; (2) how do molecular immune mechanisms respond to environmental and physiological stressors in wild populations; and (3) how do gene expression profiles and viral infection influence one another in the wild? The results should allow links to be discerned that connect environmental gradients of human disturbance to virome diversity via organismal conditions, thereby providing essential new information for understanding disease dynamics in the wild, modeling risks, and thus preventing the next pandemic. Moreover, the project’s integrated and mechanistic systems approach to studying fundamental processes in disease emergence is expected to be generalizable across taxa at the human-wildlife disease interface.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ecological constraints on highly evolvable olfactory receptor genes and morphology in neotropical bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_ecological_constraints_on_highly_evolvable_olfactor_receptor_genes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_ecological_constraints_on_highly_evolvable_olfactor_receptor_genes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nicolette Sipperly co-organized workshop on Science, Art, and You at Botany 2022</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-06-26-sipperly-botany/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-06-26-sipperly-botany/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Nicolette Sipperly co-organized and presented at the Botany 2022 Workshop &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.botanyconference.org/engine/search/index.php?func=detail&amp;amp;aid=17&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Science, Art, and You&lt;/a&gt; which enabled participants to tap into the creative process of science through art.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lexi Brown wins a Roosevelt Memorial Grant from the American Museum of Natural History</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-07-19-brown-roosevelt/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-07-19-brown-roosevelt/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lexi Brown won the American Museum of Natural History&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amnh.org/research/richard-gilder-graduate-school/academics-and-research/fellowship-and-grant-opportunities/research-grants-and-graduate-student-exchange-fellowships#theodore&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Theodore vRoosevelt Memorial Grant&lt;/a&gt;! The award will enable Lexi to sequence transcriptomes from bat auditory systems!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Achieving global biodiversity goals by 2050 requires urgent and integrated actions</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_transformative_actions_drivers_biodiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_transformative_actions_drivers_biodiversity/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrating Ecological Population and Infectious Disease Modeling: White-nose Syndrome in North American Bats and SARS-CoV-2 in Feral Cats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/thesis_in_white_nose_syndrome_sars_cov2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/thesis_in_white_nose_syndrome_sars_cov2/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kristjan Mets graduates from his Ph.D.</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-05-18-mets-hooding/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-05-18-mets-hooding/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kristjanmets.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kristjan Mets&lt;/a&gt; graduated in the Spring 2022 doctoral hooding ceremony. Dr. Mets&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;../../../publication/thesis_in_white_nose_syndrome_sars_cov2/&#34;&gt;dissertation&lt;/a&gt; explored how environmental reservoirs and between species interactions influence emergent infectious disease transmission.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Liliana Dávalos receives 2022 Award for Excellence in Assessment</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-05-05-davalos-teaching-award/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-05-05-davalos-teaching-award/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Liliana Dávalos has been awarded the 2022 Award for Excellence in Assessment at this year&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://youtu.be/4bk3rWE7DH0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;2022 Celebration of Teaching Awards&lt;/a&gt;. See the full program &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.stonybrook.edu/celt/programs-initiatives/celebration_of_teaching_awards/2022_teaching_awards&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contradictory Phylogenetic Signals in the Laurasiatheria Anomaly Zone</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_contradictory_phylogenetic_signals_laurasiatheria/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_contradictory_phylogenetic_signals_laurasiatheria/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Environmental impacts of illegal drugs in Mongabay</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-04-04-davalos-all-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-04-04-davalos-all-up/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Mongabay&amp;rsquo;s Sean Mowbray has generated a wide-ranging review of &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.mongabay.com/2022/04/all-coked-up-the-global-environmental-impacts-of-cocaine/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;environmental impacts of coca&lt;/a&gt; at every stage of the illegal drug market and its response. The review highlights deforestation dynamics from production and trafficking, including quotes from Liliana!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Co-evolution of viruses with host genome-editing enzymes in bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/biochemical_and_genomic_characterization_apobec/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/biochemical_and_genomic_characterization_apobec/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Colonial legacies influence biodiversity lessons: how past trade routes and power dynamics shape present-day scientific research and professional opportunities for Caribbean scientists</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_colonial_legacies_influence/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_colonial_legacies_influence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>William Thomas wins a EECG award from the American Genetic Association</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-03-15-thomas-eecg/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-03-15-thomas-eecg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;William Thomas won the American Genetic Association&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theaga.org/news-article/67&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Evolutionary, Ecological, or Conservation Genomics Research Award&lt;/a&gt;! Bill joins lab alumni &lt;a href=&#34;https://marisalim.weebly.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Marisa Lim&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://lauterbur.weebly.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Elise Lauterbur&lt;/a&gt; in receiving this distinction. The award will enable Bill to parse the relative importance of demography and selection as processes that shape genetic diversity in the Eurasian common shrew!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>William Thomas wins the Society for the Study of Evolution Graduate Research Excellence Grant</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-01-27-thomas-sse/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/22-01-27-thomas-sse/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;William Thomas won the Society for the Study of Evolution&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.evolutionsociety.org/society-awards-and-prizes/graduate-research-excellence-grants/rosemary-grant-advanced-award.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Graduate Research Excellence Grant&lt;/a&gt;! The award will help William generate population genomic data to discover shrew wintering adaptations!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transformative actions on all drivers of biodiversity loss are urgently required to achieve the global goals by 2050</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_transformative_actions_drivers_biodiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_transformative_actions_drivers_biodiversity/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Los fantasmas del desarrollo pasado. Deforestación y coca en la Amazonía occidental</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_fantasmas_desarrollo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_fantasmas_desarrollo/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Los orígenes de la cocaína. Colonización y desarrollo fallido en los Andes amazónicos</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/edited_books_origenes_cocaina/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/edited_books_origenes_cocaina/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Case Studies to Improve the Critical Thinking Skills of Undergraduate Conservation Biology Students</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_using_case_studies_improve_critical_thinking_skills/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_using_case_studies_improve_critical_thinking_skills/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Liliana Dávalos featured in Mongabay!</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/21-10-29-liliana-mongabay/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/21-10-29-liliana-mongabay/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bats, forests, and life in science featured in long interview for &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.mongabay.com/2021/10/to-change-policies-insert-yourself-in-them-qa-with-biologist-liliana-davalos/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mongabay&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.mongabay.com/by/nicolas-bustamante-hernandez/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nicolás Bustamante &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forests, Coca, and Conflict: Grass Frontier Dynamics and Deforestation in the Amazon-Andes</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_forests_coca_conflict_grass/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_forests_coca_conflict_grass/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dávalos Lab featured on Nova!</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/21-09-15-liliana-nova/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/21-09-15-liliana-nova/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lab &amp;amp; life partnership as well as new research featured in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pbs.org/video/bat-superpowers-nfuph6/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PBS Nova&lt;/a&gt; (go to min 7) by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.imdb.com/name/nm6815794/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Raphaël Hitier &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nectar-Feeding Bats and Birds Show Parallel Molecular Adaptations in Sugar Metabolism Enzymes</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_dietary_nectar-feedin_bats_and_birds_show_parallel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_dietary_nectar-feedin_bats_and_birds_show_parallel/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fire-induced loss of the world’s most biodiverse forests in Latin America</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_fires_latin_america/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_fires_latin_america/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fruit odorants mediate co-specialization in a multispecies plant–animal mutualism</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_fruit_odorants_mediate_cospecialization/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_fruit_odorants_mediate_cospecialization/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drug pollution &amp; sustainable development goals</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_drug_pollutions_sdgs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_drug_pollutions_sdgs/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversity in olfactory receptor repertoires is associated with dietary specialization in a genus of frugivorous bat</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_diversity_olfactory_receptors_diet_genus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_diversity_olfactory_receptors_diet_genus/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large-Scale Genome Sampling Reveals Unique Immunity and Metabolic Adaptations in Bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_genome_sampling_immunity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_genome_sampling_immunity/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Impacts of deforestation and degradation of forests and aquatic ecosystems on human well-being and health</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_human_wellbeing_health/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_human_wellbeing_health/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bats and Viruses: Current Research and Future Trends</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_bat_viruses/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_bat_viruses/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Find the Food First: An Omnivorous Sensory Morphotype Predates Biomechanical Specialization for Plant Based Diets in Phyllostomid Bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_find_food_first_omnivorous/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_find_food_first_omnivorous/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>William Thomas wins the Society for Systematic Biologists GSRA</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/21-05-14-thomas-ssb/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/21-05-14-thomas-ssb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;William Thomas won the Society for Systematic Biologists&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.systbio.org/graduate-student-research-awards.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Graduate Student Research Award&lt;/a&gt;! The award will help William generate population genetic/epigenetic data for discovering shrew wintering adaptations!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No peace for the forest: Rapid, widespread land changes in the Andes-Amazon region following the Colombian civil war</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_no_peace_for_forest/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_no_peace_for_forest/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kristjan Mets wins the Presidential Dissertation Completion Fellowship</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/21-04-30-mets-president/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/21-04-30-mets-president/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Kristjan Mets won the Presidential Dissertation Completion Fellowship! The award will help Kristjan to complete his dissertation over the summer!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where the wild things were: intrinsic and extrinsic extinction predictors in the world&#39;s most depleted mammal fauna</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_where_the_wild_things/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_where_the_wild_things/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pervasive genomic signatures of local adaptation to altitude across highland specialist Andean hummingbird populations</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_pervasive_genomic_signatures_of_local/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_pervasive_genomic_signatures_of_local/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dietary Diversification and Specialisation in New World Bats Facilitated by Early Molecular Evolution</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_dietary_diversification_specialisation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_dietary_diversification_specialisation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anna McPherran wins the Williams award</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/21-02-06-anna-williams/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/21-02-06-anna-williams/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Anna McPherran won the Williams award at the 2021 Ecology &amp;amp; Evolution retreat. The award will help Anna sequence the genomes of hutias!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Global Union of Bat Diversity Networks (GBatNet)</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/global_bat_net/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/global_bat_net/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recuadro 5.1: Los cultivos ilícitos como motor de degradación y conversión de los ecosistemas</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_recuadro_ilicitos_servicios/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_recuadro_ilicitos_servicios/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>National Geographic features research partnership</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/20-12-07-national-geographic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/20-12-07-national-geographic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://eleanorcummins.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Eleanor Cummins&lt;/a&gt; featured lab &amp;amp; life partnership as well as new research in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nationalgeographic.co.uk/science-and-technology/2020/12/bats-museums-and-viruses-collide-in-this-scientific-love-story&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;National Geographic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bats Magazine features Bat Genomes</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/20-10-24-bat-genomics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/20-10-24-bat-genomics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.christiewilcox.com/index.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Christie Wilcox&lt;/a&gt; featured new &lt;a href=&#34;files/wilcox2020.pdf&#34;&gt;genomics research&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.batcon.org/article/out-of-the-darkness/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bats Magazine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bats Magazine features PI Dávalos</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/20-10-24-bats-magazine/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/post/20-10-24-bats-magazine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://shaenamontanari.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Shaena Montanari&lt;/a&gt; featured the &lt;a href=&#34;files/montanari2020.pdf&#34;&gt;people&lt;/a&gt; behind the genome research in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.batcon.org/article/gene-genius/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bats Magazine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phyllostomid Bats: A unique Mammalian Radiation</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/edited_books_phyllostomid_bats/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/edited_books_phyllostomid_bats/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With over two-hundred species distributed across most of mainland Mexico, Central and South America, and islands in the Caribbean Sea, the Phyllostomidae bat family (American leaf-nosed bats) is one of the world’s most diverse mammalian families in terms of its trophic, or feeding, diversity. From an insectivorous ancestry, extant species have evolved into several dietary classes, including blood-feeding, vertebrate carnivory, and the consumption of nectar, pollen, and fruit, in a period of about 30 million years. Phyllostomid plant-visiting species are responsible for pollinating over five-hundred species of neotropical shrubs, trees, vines, and epiphytes—many of which are economically and ecologically important—and they also disperse the seeds of at least another five-hundred plant species. Fruit-eating and seed-dispersing members of this family thus play a crucial role in the regeneration of neotropical forests, and the fruit eaters are among the most abundant mammals in these habitats.
Coauthored by leading experts in the field and synthesizing the latest advances in molecular biology and ecological methods, Phyllostomid Bats is the first overview in more than forty years of the evolution of the many morphological, behavioral, physiological, and ecological adaptations in this family. Featuring abundant illustrations as well as details on the current classification and conservation status of phyllostomid species, it is both a comprehensive reference for these ecologically vital mammals and a fascinating exploration of the evolutionary process of adaptive radiation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adapt or Live: Adaptation, Convergent Evolution, and Plesiomorphy</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_adapt_live/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_adapt_live/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overview of This Book</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_overview_phyllostomids/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_overview_phyllostomids/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylogenetics and Historical Biogeography</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_phylogenetics_historical_biogeography/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_phylogenetics_historical_biogeography/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Handbook of the Mammals of the World. Volume 9: Bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_handbook_mammals_world/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_handbook_mammals_world/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Six reference-quality genomes reveal evolution of bat adaptations</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_six_new_reference-quality_bat_genomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_six_new_reference-quality_bat_genomes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Molecular adaptation and convergent evolution of frugivory in Old World and neotropical fruit bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_molecular_adaptation_and_convergent_evolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_molecular_adaptation_and_convergent_evolution/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pandemics’ historical role in creating inequality</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_pandemics_historical_role/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_pandemics_historical_role/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bat goblet cells as immuno-hotspots for infection of coronavirus</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/bat_goblet_cells/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/bat_goblet_cells/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immunological adaptations in bats to moderate the effect of coronavirus infection</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/immunological_adaptations_in_bats/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/immunological_adaptations_in_bats/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inter-Species Modeling for Spillback/Spillover Avoidance</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/spillback/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/spillback/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In support of RA Kristjan Mets. While scientific reaction to the COVID-19 pandemic has been swift, the risk of SARS-CoV-2 spilling back into native North American wildlife and feral domestic animals remains underexplored. Experimental infections of a variety of hosts, serological analyses of the cats in Wuhan, and cases of COVID-19 among tigers and lions in the Bronx Zoo, all have shown transmission back to wildlife and feral cats is highly probable. Tools are urgently needed to determine which of these animal populations are at greatest risk of establishing a native reservoir, and where the overlap with human populations is greatest. We propose to model the risk of spillover to animal populations and conversely the risk of future secondary spillover by combining models of molecular interaction between the virus and potential hosts, with multi- species Susceptible-Infectious-Recovered (SIR) models. Complementing decades of experience in vertebrate genomics (Dávalos) with expertise in epidemiology (Meliker), and spatial dynamics of wildlife disease (Mets), ours is the ideal team to quickly generate and test the necessary models to avert this risk.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Foraging shifts and visual preadaptation in ecologically diverse bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_foraging_shifts_and_visual_preadaptation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_foraging_shifts_and_visual_preadaptation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The allometry of daily energy expenditure in hummingbirds: an energy budget approach</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_allometry_of_daily_energy_expenditure/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_allometry_of_daily_energy_expenditure/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Species tree disequilibrium positively misleads models of gene family evolution</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/preprint_species_tree_disequilibrium/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/preprint_species_tree_disequilibrium/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Curb land grabbing to save the Amazon</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_curb_land_grabbing_to_save_the_amazon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_curb_land_grabbing_to_save_the_amazon/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tissue Collection of Bats for-Omics Analyses and Primary Cell Culture</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_tissue_collection_of_bats_for-mics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_tissue_collection_of_bats_for-mics/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating the performance of targeted sequence capture, RNA-Seq, and degenerate-primer PCR cloning for sequencing the largest mammalian multigene family</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_targeted_sequence_capture_outperforms/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_targeted_sequence_capture_outperforms/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Investment and Smallholder Coca Cultivation in Colombia</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_social_investment_and_smallholder/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_social_investment_and_smallholder/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Expressed vomeronasal type-1 receptors (V1rs) in bats uncover conserved sequences underlying social chemical signaling</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_expressed_vomeronasal_type-1_receptors/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_expressed_vomeronasal_type-1_receptors/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morphological Diversification under High Integration in a Hyper Diverse Mammal Clade</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_morphological_diversification_under_high/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_morphological_diversification_under_high/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regrowing the brain; evolution and mechanisms of seasonal reversible size changes in a mammal</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/regrowing_the_brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/regrowing_the_brain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Organisms need strategies to survive when conditions are hard. For mammals, winter is particularly difficult - they have to invest large amounts of energy into keeping warm, while food availability is low. For this reason, many mammals migrate or hibernate. However, what to do if you are too small to migrate long distance, burn your energy fast, and cannot hibernate? The common shrew is such a mammal and has evolved an astonishing strategy: each individual shrinks in winter by up to 20% and then regrows in the spring by about 13%. This size change, thought to allow shrews to survive on fewer resources because of the smaller size and linked lower energy requirements, include not just overall size, but specifically organs that do not usually change size in fully grown animals, such as the brain, heart and liver.
The process of neurological degeneration and regeneration is of great interest, since many central nervous system diseases (e.g., Alzheimer’s, multiple sclerosis) involve degeneration, but ongoing research for therapies to reverse this process has been of limited success. As one of only a few recorded examples of mammalian brain regeneration, understanding how the shrew regrows its brain can accelerate research that leads to future therapies.
To answer the question of how the shrew shrinks and then regrows its brain, we will establish this unusual species as a new model, by studying the biological, molecular, biochemical and genetic processes behind this reversible size change. Besides establishing a database of information that can be mined and researched in years to come to discover the pathways that generate this cycle in the shrew, we will test a metabolic model of neurological change by artificially blocking molecular access to fats. Thus, the cross-disciplinary study of this wintering adaptation may help us understand more about regeneration in mammals in general, and the brain in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parallel molecular evolution in pathways, genes, and sites in high-elevation hummingbirds revealed by comparative transcriptomics</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_parallel_molecular_evolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_parallel_molecular_evolution/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In Extremis: Breaking Coalescent Models in Small Populations and Concerted Convergence of Mammalian Cyanide Adaptation</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/thesis_in_extremis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/thesis_in_extremis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The death and life of biodiversity: modeling extinction and resilience on islands</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/death_and_life_of_biodiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/death_and_life_of_biodiversity/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Very Extended Phenotype: connecting genetics and evolution to ecological function</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/very_extended_phenotype/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/very_extended_phenotype/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two major recent trends in funding in biology have been integrative research that focuses on general principles that operate across levels and scales of biological systems; and research that integrates genetic, phylogenetic, and functional dimensions of the diversity of life on Earth. These two research approaches offer much promise to address not only many of the fundamental questions about life, but also many of the problems facing humanity, including the irreversible, ongoing, and rapid loss of biodiversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conservation biologists have so far focused on risks of extinction, decline and collapse of species and ecosystems, while recognizing how just avoiding loss is not enough. Until recently, the ultimate goals of biodiversity conservation—recovery and restoration—have remained difficult, elusive, and vaguely defined. Earlier this year, a new framework for assessing species recovery and conservation success has been proposed. A central concept of this framework is the ecological functionality of populations, based on the idea that conserving species requires not only avoiding extinction, but also maintaining their contributions to ecosystem processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The practical application of this framework requires fundamental research about the relationships between ecological function and other organismal and genetic dimensions of biodiversity. We propose to develop a cross-scale research program that focuses on the relationships between phylogenetic diversity, genetic diversity and functional diversity of a biologically and economically
important taxonomic group: bees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overall goal of the proposed research is to test hypotheses on the relationships among multiple dimensions of biological diversity, and their relevance for functioning of ecological communities. Our specific objectives for this OVPR Seed Proposal focus on preparing a strong initial proposal for
NSF, potentially followed by additional proposals. We aim to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Obtain preliminary genomic data via RNA transcripts and hybridization baits,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start developing a database of ecological functionality to relate species to their molecular and ecological function,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recruit collaborators to strengthen specific aspects of the planned proposal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have extensive experience in both the general subject area of the proposal, and the specific methodological and conceptual advances that underlie the proposed research program. However, we have never collaborated before, and we lack preliminary data on the system we propose to focus on. In order to build the collaboration and establish the preliminary data to successfully compete, we need the internal support provided by the OVPR seed funding. With funding from the OVPR Seed Grant Program, we plan to develop a new collaboration and a new research program that will likely lead to several externally funded projects over the coming 5-10 years. Our initial target will be the NSF program on Dimensions of Biodiversity ($2M total), but we expect that we will have multiple opportunities for external funding in the next year or so..&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fires in protected areas reveal unforseen costs of Colombian peace</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_fires_in_protected_areas/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_fires_in_protected_areas/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multifactorial processes underlie parallel opsin loss in neotropical bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_multifactorial_processes_underlie/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_multifactorial_processes_underlie/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the Evolution and Diversification of Andean Hummingbirds</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/thesis_on_the_evolution_diversification/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/thesis_on_the_evolution_diversification/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Protocols for the Molecular Evolutionary Analysis of Membrane Protein Gene Duplicates</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_protocols_molecular_evolutionary_analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_protocols_molecular_evolutionary_analysis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>BIO 211: Statistics and Data Analysis: A Conceptual Approach</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/course/18-08-26-bio-211/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/course/18-08-26-bio-211/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Currently taught by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pascaltitle.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pascal Title&lt;/a&gt;. This course is an introduction to probability and data analysis emphasizing the nature of science, statistical literacy, thinking, and reasoning. While focused on statistical concepts such as probability and distributions, examples and applications are based on competencies relevant to biological data and interpretations in light of biological models. The course applies active learning, with both lectures and recitation periods built around student engagement and hands-on activities. These include, but are not limited to, discussing the primary literature and plotting, analyzing, and interpreting published and simulated data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pre- or Corequisite: MAT 123 or higher, or level 4 or higher on the mathematics placement examination. May not be taken by students with credit in AMS 110, 310, 311, 412, EBH 230, or ECO 320&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DEC:     C&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SBC:     STEM+&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4 credits&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instructor (current): &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pascaltitle.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pascal Title&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A coalescent-based estimator of genetic drift, and acoustic divergence in the Pteronotus parnellii species complex</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_coalescent-based_estimator/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_coalescent-based_estimator/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updated distribution maps for neotropical bats in the superfamily Noctilionoidea</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_updated_distribution_maps/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_updated_distribution_maps/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genomics of exceptions to scaling of longevity to body size</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/genomics_of_exceptions_to_scaling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/genomics_of_exceptions_to_scaling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Ghosts of Development Past: Deforestation and Coca in Western Amazonia</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_ghosts_of_development_past/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_ghosts_of_development_past/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Origins of Cocaine: Colonization and Failed Development in the Amazon Andes</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/edited_books_origins_of_cocaine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/edited_books_origins_of_cocaine/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessing Soft-Tissue Shrinkage Estimates in Museum Specimens Imaged With Diffusible Iodine-based Contrast-Enhanced Computed Tomography (diceCT)</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_assessing_soft_tissue_shrinkage/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_assessing_soft_tissue_shrinkage/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Opposition Support and the Experience of Violence Explain the Colombian Peace Referendum</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_opposition_support/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_opposition_support/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vomeronasal and olfactory structures in bats revealed by diceCT clarify genetic evidence of function</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_vomeronasal_and_olfactory_structures/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_vomeronasal_and_olfactory_structures/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strength of selection on the Trpc2 gene predicts accessory olfactory bulb form in bat vomeronasal evolution</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_genetic_function_of_trpc2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_genetic_function_of_trpc2/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying municipal risk factors for leftist guerrilla violence in Colombia</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_identifying_municipal_risk_factors/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_identifying_municipal_risk_factors/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bat Biology, Genomes, and the Bat1K Project: to generate chromosome-level genomes for all living bat species</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_bat_biology_genomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_bat_biology_genomes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Out of the Antilles: Fossil Phylogenies Support Reverse Colonization of Bats to South America</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_out_of_the_antilles/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_out_of_the_antilles/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eating down the food chain: generalism is not an evolutionary dead end for herbivores</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_eating_down_the_food_chain/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_eating_down_the_food_chain/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A communal catalogue reveals Earth’s multiscale microbial diversity</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_communal_catalogue_reveals_earth/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_communal_catalogue_reveals_earth/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anthropogenic Extinction Dominates Holocene Declines of West Indian Mammals</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_anthropogenic_extinction_dominates/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_anthropogenic_extinction_dominates/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial autocorrelation reduces model precision and predictive power in deforestation analyses</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_spatial_autocorrelation_reduces/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_spatial_autocorrelation_reduces/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Molecular Evolution of Bat Chemosensory Pathways Reveals Sensory Innovation and Loss</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/thesis_molecular_evolution_of_bat/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/thesis_molecular_evolution_of_bat/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrating remotely sensed fires for predicting deforestation for REDD&#43;</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_integrating_remotely_sensed_fires/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_integrating_remotely_sensed_fires/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trpc2 pseudogenization dynamics in bats reveal ancestral vomeronasal signaling, then pervasive loss</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_trpc2_pseudogenization_dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_trpc2_pseudogenization_dynamics/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent extinctions disturb path to equilibrium diversity in Caribbean bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_recent_extinctions_disturb_path/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_recent_extinctions_disturb_path/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deforestation and Coca Cultivation Rooted in Twentieth-Century Development Projects</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_deforestation_and_coca_cultivation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_deforestation_and_coca_cultivation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interdisciplinary Graduate Training to Understand and Inform Decision Processes Using Advanced Spatial Data Analysis and Visualization</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/spatial_data_analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/spatial_data_analysis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The world drug problem and sustainable development</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_world_drug_problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_world_drug_problem/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Records of the cave-dwelling bats (Mammalia: Chiroptera) of Hispaniola with an examination of seasonal variation in diversity</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_records_of_the_cave-dwelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_records_of_the_cave-dwelling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylogeny and divergence times of lemurs inferred with recent and ancient fossils in the tree</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_phylogeny_and_divergence_times/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_phylogeny_and_divergence_times/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bats (Chiroptera: Noctilionoidea) Challenge a Recent Origin of Extant Neotropical Diversity</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_bats_chiroptera_noctilionoidea/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_bats_chiroptera_noctilionoidea/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian hierarchical models suggest oldest known plant-visiting bat was omnivorous</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_bayesian_hierarchical_models_suggest/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_bayesian_hierarchical_models_suggest/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Bayesian Spatial Model Highlights Distinct Dynamics in Deforestation from Coca and Pastures in an Andean Biodiversity Hotspot</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_a_bayesian_spatial_model_highlights/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_a_bayesian_spatial_model_highlights/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amino acid transporter expansions associated with the evolution of obligate endosymbiosis in sap-feeding insects (Hemiptera: Sternorrhyncha)</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_amino_acid_transporters_expansion/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_amino_acid_transporters_expansion/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From the Field to the Lab: Best Practices for Field Preservation of Bat Specimens for Molecular Analyses</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_from_the_field_to_the_lab/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_from_the_field_to_the_lab/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chance or necessity? Adaptive vs. non adaptive evolution in plant-frugivore interactions</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/chance_or_necessity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/chance_or_necessity/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Molecular evolution of growth hormone and insulin-like growth factor 1 receptors in long-lived, small-bodied mammals</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_molecular_evolution_of_growth_hormone/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_molecular_evolution_of_growth_hormone/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering genomic and developmental mechanisms that underlie sensory innovations critical to adaptive diversification</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/discovering_genomic_and_developmental_mechanisms/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/discovering_genomic_and_developmental_mechanisms/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sex-biased dispersal produces high error rates in mitochondrial distance-based and tree-based species delimitation</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_sex_biased_dispersal_produces/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_sex_biased_dispersal_produces/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrating Incomplete Fossils by Isolating Conflicting Signal in Saturated and Non-Independent Morphological Characters</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_integrating_incomplete_fossils/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_integrating_incomplete_fossils/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Uncovering skin immune proteins as predictors of resistance against WNS</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/uncovering_skin_immune_proteins/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/uncovering_skin_immune_proteins/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic recruitment of amino acid transporters to the insect/symbiont interface</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_dynamic_recruitment_of_amino_acid_transporters/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_dynamic_recruitment_of_amino_acid_transporters/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Demand for beef is unrelated to pasture expansion in northwestern Amazonia</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_demand_for_beef/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_demand_for_beef/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Cluster of Olfactory Receptor Genes Linked to Frugivory in Bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_a_cluster_of_olfactory_receptor_genes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_a_cluster_of_olfactory_receptor_genes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Selection for mechanical advantage underlies multiple cranial optima in new world leaf-nosed bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_selection_for_mechanical_advantage/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_selection_for_mechanical_advantage/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An horizon scan of biogeography</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_an_horizon_scan/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_an_horizon_scan/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deglaciation explains bat extinction in the Caribbean</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_deglaciation_explains_bat_extinction/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_deglaciation_explains_bat_extinction/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An apparent hybrid Heliodoxa hummingbird from the West Andes of Colombia</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_apparent_hybrid_heliodoxa/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_apparent_hybrid_heliodoxa/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Understanding phylogenetic incongruence: lessons from phyllostomid bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_understanding_phylogenetic_incongruence/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_understanding_phylogenetic_incongruence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detecting the Immune System Response of a 500 Year-Old Inca Mummy</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_detecting_the_immune_system_response/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_detecting_the_immune_system_response/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>West Indian Mammals: the Old, the New, and the Recently Extinct</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_west_indian_mammals/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_west_indian_mammals/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morphological innovation, diversification and invasion of a new adaptive zone</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_morphological_innovation_diversification/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_morphological_innovation_diversification/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keeping it simple: flowering plants tend to retain, and revert to, simple leaves</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_keeping_it_simple/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_keeping_it_simple/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forests and Drugs: Coca-Driven Deforestation in Tropical Biodiversity Hotspots</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_forests_and_drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_forests_and_drugs/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>El Callejón de los Milagros</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_el_callejon_de_los_milagros/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_el_callejon_de_los_milagros/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The river-refuge hypothesis and other contributions of Márcio Ayres to conservation science</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_river_refuge_hypothesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Nov 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_river_refuge_hypothesis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Earth history and the evolution of Caribbean bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_earth_history_evolution_caribbean_bats/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_earth_history_evolution_caribbean_bats/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disabusing cocaine: Pervasive myths and enduring realities of a globalised commodity</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_disabusing_cocaine/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_disabusing_cocaine/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accounting for molecular stochasticity in systematic revisions: Species limits and phylogeny of Paroaria</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_accounting_for_molecular_stochasticity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_accounting_for_molecular_stochasticity/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversification in Noctilionoid Bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/diversification_of_noctilionoid_bats/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/diversification_of_noctilionoid_bats/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New species of Lonchophylla ‪(‬Chiroptera, Phyllostomidae‪)‬ from the eastern Andes of northwestern South America</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_new_species_lonchophylla/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_new_species_lonchophylla/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saturation and base composition bias explain phylogenomic conflict in Plasmodium</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_saturation_and_base_composition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_saturation_and_base_composition/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conservation in conflict: illegal drugs versus habitat in the Americas</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_conservation_in_conflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_conservation_in_conflict/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short‐faced bats (Phyllostomidae: Stenodermatina): a Caribbean radiation of strict frugivores</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_short_faced_bats/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_short_faced_bats/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Environmental damage from illicit drug crops in Colombia</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_environmental_damage_illicit_drug_crops/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_environmental_damage_illicit_drug_crops/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The geography of diversification in the mormoopids (Chiroptera: Mormoopidae)</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_geography_diversification_mormoopids/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_geography_diversification_mormoopids/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Nature and Dynamics of Bacterial Genomes</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_nature_dynamics_bacterial_genomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_nature_dynamics_bacterial_genomes/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Molecular phylogeny of funnel-eared bats (Chiroptera: Natalidae), with notes on biogeography and conservation</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_molecular_phylogeny_funnel-eared_bats/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_molecular_phylogeny_funnel-eared_bats/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Illicit Crops and Armed Conflict as Constraints on Biodiversity Conservation in the Andes Region</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_illicit_crops_armed_conflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_illicit_crops_armed_conflict/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bats of Puerto Rico</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_bats_of_puerto_rico/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_bats_of_puerto_rico/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Colombia: the many faces of the war</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_colombia_many_faces_of_war/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_colombia_many_faces_of_war/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guerrillas in the midst</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_guerrillas_in_the_midst/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_guerrillas_in_the_midst/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring population genetic structure in three species of Lesser Antillean bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_exploring_population_genetic_structure_three/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_exploring_population_genetic_structure_three/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylogeny of the Lonchophyllini (Chiroptera: Phyllostomidae)</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_phylogeny_of_lonchophyllini/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_phylogeny_of_lonchophyllini/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Historical biogeography of the Antilles: Earth history and phylogenetics of endemic chiropteran taxa</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/thesis_historical_biogeography_antilles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/thesis_historical_biogeography_antilles/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylogeny and biogeography of Caribbean mammals</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_phylogeny_and_biogeography_caribbean/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_phylogeny_and_biogeography_caribbean/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A New Chocoan Species of Lonchophylla (Chiroptera: Phyllostomidae)</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_new_chocoan_species_of_lonchophylla/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_new_chocoan_species_of_lonchophylla/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epicrates subflavus (Jamaican Boa), Foraging behavior</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_epicrates_subflavus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_epicrates_subflavus/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geographical sampling bias and its implications for conservation priorities in Africa</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_geographical_sampling_bias/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_geographical_sampling_bias/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forests in the Time of Violence: Conservation Implications of the Colombian War</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_forests_in_time_of_violence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/book_section_forests_in_time_of_violence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regulating access to genetic resources under the Convention on Biological Diversity: an analysis of selected case studies</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_regulating_access_to_genetic_resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_regulating_access_to_genetic_resources/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forests in the Time of Violence; Conservation Implications of the Colombian War</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_forests_in_the_time_of_violence/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_forests_in_the_time_of_violence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New and Noteworthy Records from Ten Jamaican Bat Caves</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_new_noteworthy_records_ten_jamaican_bat_caves/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_new_noteworthy_records_ten_jamaican_bat_caves/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Illicit Crops and Bird Conservation Priorities in Colombia</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_illicit_crops_bird_conservation_priorities/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2002 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_illicit_crops_bird_conservation_priorities/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Historical Biogeography of the Antilles</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/historical_biogeography_antilles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2002 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/historical_biogeography_antilles/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Could Peace be Worse than War for Colombia&#39;s Forests?</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_could_peace_be_worse_than_war/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_could_peace_be_worse_than_war/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Missing the Forest for the Profits: The Role of Multinational Corporations in the International Forest Regime</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_missing_the_forest_for_the_profits/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_missing_the_forest_for_the_profits/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Parc National La Visite, Haiti a last refuge for the country&#39;s montane birds</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_parc_national_la_visite/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_parc_national_la_visite/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The birds of Ile-a-Vache, Haiti</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_birds_of_ile-a-vache/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_birds_of_ile-a-vache/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title> Daños ambientales por cultivos ilícitos y procesamiento de drogas prohibidas en Colombia</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_danos_ambientales_por_cultivos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_danos_ambientales_por_cultivos/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forests under fire</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_forests_under_fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_forests_under_fire/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Serranía de San Lucas, Sur de Bolívar: ¿Habrá futuro?</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_serrania_de_san_lucas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_serrania_de_san_lucas/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The San Lucas mountain range in Colombia how much conservation is owed to the violence?</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_san_lucas_mountain_range/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_san_lucas_mountain_range/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>La perspectiva ambiental en la mesa de diálogo</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_la_perspectiva_ambiental/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2000 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_la_perspectiva_ambiental/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>El Futuro de los bosques de Colombia: ¿será la paz peor que la guerra?</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_el_futuro_de_los_bosques/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2000 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_el_futuro_de_los_bosques/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ornithological observations from Reserva Natural Tambito, Cauca, south-west Colombia</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_ornithological_observations_reserva_natural_tambito/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 1999 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_ornithological_observations_reserva_natural_tambito/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The bat fauna of Tambito, Colombia</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_bat_fauna_tambito_colombia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 1999 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_bat_fauna_tambito_colombia/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Access to Genetic Resources: An Evaluation of the Development and Implementation of Recent Regulation and Access Agreements</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_access_to_genetic_resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 1999 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_access_to_genetic_resources/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Birds-Aves</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_birds-aves/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1998 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/misc_birds-aves/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The first breeding records of white-rimmed brush-finch Atlapetes leucopis with ecological notes</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_first_breeding_records_white_rimmed_brush_finch/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 1998 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/journal_first_breeding_records_white_rimmed_brush_finch/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marcadores moleculares asociados a resistencia al virus de la hoja blanca de arroz (Oryza sativa L.)</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/thesis_marcadores_moleculares/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 1997 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/thesis_marcadores_moleculares/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/admin/config.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/admin/config.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
