<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:iphoto="urn:iphoto:property" xmlns:iweb="http://www.apple.com/iweb" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Looking for forest in Haiti</title>
    <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti.html</link>
    <description>since every airport in the US notes that Port au Prince's airport does not meet safety standards, i was very curious to see what kind of place it was. i could not figure out exactly why it was blacklisted. it's basically a small-town airport with little or no amenities, not even a bureau de change, but my hypothesis is that the unpredictable blackouts have rendered gun detectors and x-ray machines useless. much to my dismay, i was singled out at the immigration queue as i showed my burgundy Colombian passport, and taken to a small dingy room by a lady who said &quot;pas problem&quot; while i stood waiting for my passport to return. after about ten minutes it was returned to me and i was allowed to leave.
&#13;we paid an unreasonably expensive cab to the bus station (no actual building), noting that; a. the road into town is not completely paved, b. PaP is a huge, noisy, very active city. the driver escorted us to the station, or rather the place where buses (taptaps) congregate. the taptap he (very helpfully) chose for us seems to have been selected on the basis of how large the speaker in the passengers' cabin was (3 x 2 x 1 ft). the pain of the Ayitian music blaring out of the speaker was only relieved by a vehement preacher who quickly got on the nerves of several people, prompting the return of &quot;Papillon&quot; (Colombians note there were some creole versions of Carlos Vives songs!). other typical taptap behaviours include driving exactly in the middle of the road and honking (minimum 10 seconds every time) to signal overtaking, turns, or scare people, dogs, goats, pigs etc. off the road.
&#13;we arrived at Aux Cayes (southeast coastal town) and looked for a boat to take us to Île-à-Vache. there we met Emilio: a 65 yo character who would have taken us to the island, had he not got in trouble with his wife for having a mistress on the Île. he highly recommended going on to the island as it was touristy and had lots of internationals, including a (dodgy?) Colombian investor. when we asked about the natural habitat (forest?) the response was a blank stare. relentless, we pushed on. the public motorboat we used was overloaded by a factor of 2, but the sea was very calm and we had no reason to be scared, since we both could swim. unfortunately the boatman was trying to rip us off (by a factor of 15) on the price of the ride, but the girl squeezed next to me signalled the correct price to me and we refused to pay what he demanded.
&#13;Île-à-Vache is as unspoiled and beautiful as Caribbean islands get. the native arid scrub is almost all gone, but the native mangrove and numerous house gardens provide home to some of the lowland Hispaniola endemics. we found a nesting colony of 100 Black-crowned Night-Herons and from a high point selected a deserted beach to camp out for New Year's. the beach was postcard beauty, white sand and light azure sea with artisanal sailboats in the distance. we walked a lot around the island, meeting the locals on the trails (and realizing how densely populated the island was). everyone was very friendly, smiling, and always willing to point one in the right direction (with or without expecting compensation). most people were busy painting their houses and the tombs around them in preparation for the new year and independence celebration. at this point of the trip i was still happy disclosing my nationality when asked. that is, until i did it at Île-à-Vache and a crowd of children gathered around us, half smiling, half begging, but certainly causing a raucous. after that, i was happy with saying i came from New York or not chiming in (as i had before) when the question was posed to my companion, but not to me. sadly, the Ile has become a source of charcoal for the insatiable fuel wood market at Aux Cayes. although not considered threatened, the days of the mangroves at Île-à-Vache are numbered.
&#13;after about three days in this paradise we rented a fisherman's sailboat back to Aux Cayes for a small price, since there was no commercial service on New Year's day. from there, we went to Kenscoff (the Switzerland of Ayiti) noting in the passing that Pétionville was the poshest place in all Ayiti. from there we trekked for eight hours (eight!) to the Parc National La Visite. the north side of the mountain range is rugged, steep and utterly barren. the mountains are bare, and when i say bare i mean void of a single blade of grass, giant heaps of red earth where peasants try to scrape a crop or two. but there were far more people than crops, and it was on this trail that our stamina was really tested by constant begging, the heat of the sun and the near absence of food or water. interestingly, women and children carried the heaviest loads of carrots and other produce, while men often travelled with a tiny plastic bag in their hand, looking clean and sharp. the locals probably thought we were very dumb for carrying the load on our backs and not our heads, and expecting (as i did) the male to carry the lot of it.
&#13;the park is what's left of the native pine forest with its dose of higher elevation endemics. the forest remnant is criss-crossed by trails for pacing cows, and selective cutting and burning is taking place presumably to expand the pastures since pinewood is no good for charcoal. we camped for a night but cold, hunger and exhaustion drove us to pay for our second night at the private Auberge de La Visite. the shelter can safely claim to be the only accommodation with warm water in Ayiti. in this remote, secluded place, the veil of mystery surrounding the Colombia-related episodes was lifted when the owner of the auberge, Winnie, mentioned that mine was the only country helping poor Ayiti. why, Colombia has vibrant investments that literally change the status of peasants from rags to riches in a snap. drug money (from Cali, more specifically) pervades many activities in this chronically depressed country. in contrast, other countries like Venezuela sell (sell!) petroleum to Ayiti when the black republic provided asylum and men for the Libertador's army fighting the Spanish. these kind of historical facts are not forgotten in Ayiti. so there, no wonder i got stopped at the airport, for all the authorities know i could be the next Pablo Escobar entering the country!&#13;we walked back down to Jacmel at the south side of the range. sheltered (and maybe colonized more recently), this valley is as different from the north side as heaven is from hell. some forest patches remain and gardens surround the houses sitting on fertile land planted with citrus and coffee. the trail was very steep as it descends to sea level from 2600 metres in one go (where the way up went from Kenscoff at 2000 m over four ranges). when we reached a taptap post i was barely able to walk and was ready to knick somebody's bicycle, such was the strain in my leg muscles. Jacmel is an old town where the faded glory of its buildings attest to better days now gone, and is decorated by a few European expatriates and many craft shops.
&#13;from there we hired a car to PaP which turned out to be more eventful than expected. upon the sight of a police roadblock, the chauffeur immediately came to us saying that his plates were not up to date and his car would get seized. since the last thing we wanted was to get off and look for transportation in a dark road outside PaP with our backpacks, we said that was his problem, with $80 in his pocket he might very well bribe his way through (mea culpa). he then said his aide's wife was ill and in the hospital and they needed to get back to Jacmel. curiously enough his aide seemed most concerned with looking cool wearing his sunglasses and fisherman's hat at night! the driver finally gave in and probably paid his way through. in PaP we were stopped again and this time they wanted to see ids and passports. for one time i was glad to be a woman and therefore invisible, and not have to show mine. 15 minutes away from the airport the car was finally seized and the driver was honourable enough to find another car for us. the ride also convinced us of the sad truth: PaP has no redeeming features, it is a huge, sprawling city, a disproportionate open sewer where only a little fraction of the people have electricity and public lighting is unknown.&#13;
despite this major drawback, there are many things that make Ayiti definitely worthwhile (not delving into the birds): except for PaP, crime is not an issue anywhere. as a Colombian, one appreciates the marvel of not feeling threatened and unsafe among the crowds, on trails, in solitary places. although our trip focused mostly on landscape and what's left of natural habitat, Ayiti's culture is perhaps the greatest asset. despite our faltering french (and the fact that most people don't even speak it for starters) Ayitians went out of their way to help us. smiles and greetings are the rule, not the exception. celebrations and carnivals punctuate the day-to-day activities.&#13;and of course the Hispaniolan endemic birds (some are scantily recorded in Ayiti) and the Solenodon (we saw lots of Rattus but someday will look for it) are waiting for everyone, this trip was certainly the New Year's of a millennium!</description>
    <item>
      <title>No life savers here!</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti.html#0</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">65e47904-6cc8-4365-b984-b7e540de2e51</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/overloaded/overloaded.jpg" length="19500" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/overloaded/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/overloaded/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/overloaded/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;No life savers here!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From the rolling hills...</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti.html#1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">813bc88a-52e5-4d8a-8e34-78d724b274ae</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/unspoiled/unspoiled.jpg" length="31898" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/unspoiled/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/unspoiled/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/unspoiled/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;From the rolling hills...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To the empty beach with sailboats in the distance</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti.html#2</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">cec93d9e-2848-46cf-ac67-cc7d850e7142</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/beautiful/beautiful.jpg" length="37664" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/beautiful/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/beautiful/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/beautiful/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;To the empty beach with sailboats in the distance&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The black spots in the sky are actually Black-capped Night-Herons</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti.html#3</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">f090ed94-f266-475d-bccf-5f4edfe33299</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/colony/colony.jpg" length="40053" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/colony/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/colony/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/colony/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;The black spots in the sky are actually Black-capped Night-Herons&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tourists here don't get to see the half-empty glass</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti.html#4</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">720367cb-c1cd-47bf-bee0-fa13d3a0b88a</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/postcard/postcard.jpg" length="41705" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/postcard/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/postcard/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/postcard/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;Tourists here don't get to see the half-empty glass&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A large mangrove forest was still there</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti.html#5</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">e4613d38-fd68-4f40-8d88-7e84aef6ed21</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/mangroves/mangroves.jpg" length="44273" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/mangroves/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/mangroves/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/mangroves/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;A large mangrove forest was still there&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The future of the mangroves on the Île?</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti.html#6</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1261c6bc-a6f0-4f2c-b4df-8c58787e59e9</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/charcoal/charcoal.jpg" length="66439" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/charcoal/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/charcoal/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/charcoal/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;The future of the mangroves on the Île?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A better traveling arrangement than the last one! And then the *&gt;%^@?$&lt;*&amp; camera died...</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti.html#7</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1476124c-76fe-4719-9e68-d86850aa0df7</guid>
      <enclosure url="https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/boat/boat.jpg" length="36213" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/boat/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/boat/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>https://lmdavalos.github.io/public/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Haiti_files/Media/boat/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;A better traveling arrangement than the last one! And then the *&amp;gt;%^@?$&amp;lt;*&amp;amp; camera died...&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
