<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Dávalos Lab</title>
    <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© L. Dávalos 2019-2023</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrated mechanisms of environment-host-virome interactions</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/integrated_mechanisms_environment_host_virome/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/integrated_mechanisms_environment_host_virome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Human disruption of the environment is thought to play a central role in disease emergence in wildlife populations by reducing the availability of foods and refuge that animals rely upon, thereby stressing the animals and making them more susceptible to viruses. However, the mechanisms governing relationships among the environment, the wildlife host, and the viral communities they support are poorly known. To address this problem, the project will take advantage of a single cohesive wild system of Egyptian fruit bats (Rousettus aegyptiacus) to sample animals of different sex, age, and reproductive condition from caves that support different numbers of bats, are subject to variable levels of hunting, and are surrounded by different qualities of foraging habitat and hence food resources. Using each individual bat as the unit of observation, analyses will aim to relate landscape resources, and individual condition and immunity to viral profiles, thus answering three key questions: (1) how do host abundance, reproduction, age, and condition differentially or interactively influence viral diversity; (2) how do molecular immune mechanisms respond to environmental and physiological stressors in wild populations; and (3) how do gene expression profiles and viral infection influence one another in the wild? The results should allow links to be discerned that connect environmental gradients of human disturbance to virome diversity via organismal conditions, thereby providing essential new information for understanding disease dynamics in the wild, modeling risks, and thus preventing the next pandemic. Moreover, the project’s integrated and mechanistic systems approach to studying fundamental processes in disease emergence is expected to be generalizable across taxa at the human-wildlife disease interface.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Global Union of Bat Diversity Networks (GBatNet)</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/global_bat_net/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/global_bat_net/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bat goblet cells as immuno-hotspots for infection of coronavirus</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/bat_goblet_cells/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/bat_goblet_cells/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immunological adaptations in bats to moderate the effect of coronavirus infection</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/immunological_adaptations_in_bats/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/immunological_adaptations_in_bats/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inter-Species Modeling for Spillback/Spillover Avoidance</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/spillback/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/spillback/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In support of RA Kristjan Mets. While scientific reaction to the COVID-19 pandemic has been swift, the risk of SARS-CoV-2 spilling back into native North American wildlife and feral domestic animals remains underexplored. Experimental infections of a variety of hosts, serological analyses of the cats in Wuhan, and cases of COVID-19 among tigers and lions in the Bronx Zoo, all have shown transmission back to wildlife and feral cats is highly probable. Tools are urgently needed to determine which of these animal populations are at greatest risk of establishing a native reservoir, and where the overlap with human populations is greatest. We propose to model the risk of spillover to animal populations and conversely the risk of future secondary spillover by combining models of molecular interaction between the virus and potential hosts, with multi- species Susceptible-Infectious-Recovered (SIR) models. Complementing decades of experience in vertebrate genomics (Dávalos) with expertise in epidemiology (Meliker), and spatial dynamics of wildlife disease (Mets), ours is the ideal team to quickly generate and test the necessary models to avert this risk.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regrowing the brain; evolution and mechanisms of seasonal reversible size changes in a mammal</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/regrowing_the_brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/regrowing_the_brain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Organisms need strategies to survive when conditions are hard. For mammals, winter is particularly difficult - they have to invest large amounts of energy into keeping warm, while food availability is low. For this reason, many mammals migrate or hibernate. However, what to do if you are too small to migrate long distance, burn your energy fast, and cannot hibernate? The common shrew is such a mammal and has evolved an astonishing strategy: each individual shrinks in winter by up to 20% and then regrows in the spring by about 13%. This size change, thought to allow shrews to survive on fewer resources because of the smaller size and linked lower energy requirements, include not just overall size, but specifically organs that do not usually change size in fully grown animals, such as the brain, heart and liver.
The process of neurological degeneration and regeneration is of great interest, since many central nervous system diseases (e.g., Alzheimer’s, multiple sclerosis) involve degeneration, but ongoing research for therapies to reverse this process has been of limited success. As one of only a few recorded examples of mammalian brain regeneration, understanding how the shrew regrows its brain can accelerate research that leads to future therapies.
To answer the question of how the shrew shrinks and then regrows its brain, we will establish this unusual species as a new model, by studying the biological, molecular, biochemical and genetic processes behind this reversible size change. Besides establishing a database of information that can be mined and researched in years to come to discover the pathways that generate this cycle in the shrew, we will test a metabolic model of neurological change by artificially blocking molecular access to fats. Thus, the cross-disciplinary study of this wintering adaptation may help us understand more about regeneration in mammals in general, and the brain in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The death and life of biodiversity: modeling extinction and resilience on islands</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/death_and_life_of_biodiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/death_and_life_of_biodiversity/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Very Extended Phenotype: connecting genetics and evolution to ecological function</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/very_extended_phenotype/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/very_extended_phenotype/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two major recent trends in funding in biology have been integrative research that focuses on general principles that operate across levels and scales of biological systems; and research that integrates genetic, phylogenetic, and functional dimensions of the diversity of life on Earth. These two research approaches offer much promise to address not only many of the fundamental questions about life, but also many of the problems facing humanity, including the irreversible, ongoing, and rapid loss of biodiversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conservation biologists have so far focused on risks of extinction, decline and collapse of species and ecosystems, while recognizing how just avoiding loss is not enough. Until recently, the ultimate goals of biodiversity conservation—recovery and restoration—have remained difficult, elusive, and vaguely defined. Earlier this year, a new framework for assessing species recovery and conservation success has been proposed. A central concept of this framework is the ecological functionality of populations, based on the idea that conserving species requires not only avoiding extinction, but also maintaining their contributions to ecosystem processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The practical application of this framework requires fundamental research about the relationships between ecological function and other organismal and genetic dimensions of biodiversity. We propose to develop a cross-scale research program that focuses on the relationships between phylogenetic diversity, genetic diversity and functional diversity of a biologically and economically
important taxonomic group: bees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overall goal of the proposed research is to test hypotheses on the relationships among multiple dimensions of biological diversity, and their relevance for functioning of ecological communities. Our specific objectives for this OVPR Seed Proposal focus on preparing a strong initial proposal for
NSF, potentially followed by additional proposals. We aim to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Obtain preliminary genomic data via RNA transcripts and hybridization baits,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start developing a database of ecological functionality to relate species to their molecular and ecological function,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recruit collaborators to strengthen specific aspects of the planned proposal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have extensive experience in both the general subject area of the proposal, and the specific methodological and conceptual advances that underlie the proposed research program. However, we have never collaborated before, and we lack preliminary data on the system we propose to focus on. In order to build the collaboration and establish the preliminary data to successfully compete, we need the internal support provided by the OVPR seed funding. With funding from the OVPR Seed Grant Program, we plan to develop a new collaboration and a new research program that will likely lead to several externally funded projects over the coming 5-10 years. Our initial target will be the NSF program on Dimensions of Biodiversity ($2M total), but we expect that we will have multiple opportunities for external funding in the next year or so..&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genomics of exceptions to scaling of longevity to body size</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/genomics_of_exceptions_to_scaling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/genomics_of_exceptions_to_scaling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interdisciplinary Graduate Training to Understand and Inform Decision Processes Using Advanced Spatial Data Analysis and Visualization</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/spatial_data_analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/spatial_data_analysis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chance or necessity? Adaptive vs. non adaptive evolution in plant-frugivore interactions</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/chance_or_necessity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/chance_or_necessity/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering genomic and developmental mechanisms that underlie sensory innovations critical to adaptive diversification</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/discovering_genomic_and_developmental_mechanisms/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/discovering_genomic_and_developmental_mechanisms/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Uncovering skin immune proteins as predictors of resistance against WNS</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/uncovering_skin_immune_proteins/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/uncovering_skin_immune_proteins/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diversification in Noctilionoid Bats</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/diversification_of_noctilionoid_bats/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/diversification_of_noctilionoid_bats/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Historical Biogeography of the Antilles</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/historical_biogeography_antilles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2002 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/project/historical_biogeography_antilles/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
