<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>current on D치valos Lab</title>
    <link>/tags/current/</link>
    <description>Recent content in current on D치valos Lab</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; L. D치valos 2019-present</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/current/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Bat goblet cells as immuno-hotspots for infection of coronavirus</title>
      <link>/project/bat_goblet_cells/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/bat_goblet_cells/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Immunological adaptations in bats to moderate the effect of coronavirus infection</title>
      <link>/project/immunological_adaptations_in_bats-/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/immunological_adaptations_in_bats-/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inter-Species Modeling for Spillback/Spillover Avoidance</title>
      <link>/project/spillback/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/spillback/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In support of RA Kristjan Mets. While scientific reaction to the COVID-19 pandemic has been swift, the risk of SARS-CoV-2 spilling back into native North American wildlife and feral domestic animals remains underexplored. Experimental infections of a variety of hosts, serological analyses of the cats in Wuhan, and cases of COVID-19 among tigers and lions in the Bronx Zoo, all have shown transmission back to wildlife and feral cats is highly probable. Tools are urgently needed to determine which of these animal populations are at greatest risk of establishing a native reservoir, and where the overlap with human populations is greatest. We propose to model the risk of spillover to animal populations and conversely the risk of future secondary spillover by combining models of molecular interaction between the virus and potential hosts, with multi- species Susceptible-Infectious-Recovered (SIR) models. Complementing decades of experience in vertebrate genomics (Da패valos) with expertise in epidemiology (Meliker), and spatial dynamics of wildlife disease (Mets), ours is the ideal team to quickly generate and test the necessary models to avert this risk.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regrowing the brain; evolution and mechanisms of seasonal reversible size changes in a mammal</title>
      <link>/project/regrowing_the_brain/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/regrowing_the_brain/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The death and life of biodiversity; modeling extinction and resilience on islands</title>
      <link>/project/death_and_life_of_biodiversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/death_and_life_of_biodiversity/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Genomics of exceptions to scaling of longevity to body size</title>
      <link>/project/genomics_of_exceptions_to_scaling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/genomics_of_exceptions_to_scaling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interdisciplinary Graduate Training to Understand and Inform Decision Processes Using Advanced Spatial Data Analysis and Visualization</title>
      <link>/project/spatial_data_analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/spatial_data_analysis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering genomic and developmental mechanisms that underlie sensory innovations critical to adaptive diversification</title>
      <link>/project/discovering_genomic_and_developmental_mechanisms/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/discovering_genomic_and_developmental_mechanisms/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
