<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:iphoto="urn:iphoto:property" xmlns:iweb="http://www.apple.com/iweb" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Biological diversity survey of a lowland site in the Colombian Chocó: a project proposed in 1998, one survey conducted at Tambito in 1999

Report to the Explorers’ Club</title>
    <link>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito.html</link>
    <description>Note: crossed out font has been revised on 20 Nov 2011, clarifications are in brackets.

Introduction&#13;
Northern Andean montane and tropical lowland forests are currently one of the major conservation priorities on a global scale due to their fragility, biological richness, high rates of endemism and the multiple anthropogenic threats impending their degradation (Olson and Dinerstein 1997). The northernmost part of the Andes -mostly located in Colombia- is subdivided into three mountain ranges that generate a very complex geographical pattern of exceptional biological diversity (McNeely et al. 1990, Stattersfield et al. 1997). The Colombian Andes are also the most densely populated areas in the country (CIESIN 1998), hence the last remnants of Andean and adjacent lowland forests are priorities in the national (IVH 1997, Martha Suárez personal communication) and international conservation agenda (Mary Louise Higgins personal communication).
&#13;The Chocó lowland rainforest was regarded by Chapman (1917) as &quot;the most circumscribed and sharply defined, and possibly the most strongly characterized of any fauna of South America&quot;. To date, it remains so understudied in its notable diversity, that it prompted Gentry to state in 1992 that &quot;we know more about the moon than about the Chocó&quot; (EcoLógica 1992) [similar quotes about Borneo by Myers, ultimate source has not been tracked down]. The Chocó is characterized by pockets of endemism along both the latitudinal gradient and the Pacific slope of the West Andes, that account for an extraordinary overall diversity (Lellinger 1975, Gentry 1982, Cracraft 1985).
&#13;At present, there are eight state-protected areas in the Colombian Chocó encompassing around 200 000 ha. Of these, only three -Katíos, Sanquianga and Utría- comprise lowland forest, the other five are montane and pre-montane forest exclusively. However, current threats to the Chocó are most pressing in the lowlands with the expansion of human settlement and activities such as gold mining, cattle ranching, and logging estimated at 1 million trees per year (UniValle 1994). The political agenda of regional development plans, such as dams, roads, pipelines and military installations poses further tension on the remaining tracts (Dinerstein 1995), catalogued for the most part as frontier forest (Bryant et al. 1997) meaning that it is still able to sustain its populations of native flora and fauna.&#13;Clearly, both montane and lowland forests in the Chocó are under multiple complex social, economic and political pressures that call for rapid conservation action. These actions, however, do not take place in a vacuum and cooperation with local communities is essential if any long-term conservation is going to take place (Western and Wright 1995). That is why conservation efforts should account, not only for scientific observations, but also for actual collaboration with well-acknowledged local partners conducive to protection and stewardship of the forest (Redford and Mansour 1996).   
The Uribe trail is an access route to the Pacific built during the Thousand-Day War about a century ago beginning at c. 2 600 m elevation in Uribe and descending to López de Micay (c. 200 m) in the Cauca department, South-West Colombia. Forest types range from very humid montane -&quot;cloud&quot;- forest to very humid lowland rainforest (Holdridge 1967). As the Thousand-Day War subsided, the trail was abandoned by the public and is maintained once a year by the Munchique National Natural Park staff. This trail constitutes an unparalleled accessible transect along a presumably biologically rich tract of continuous forest, comprising montane, premontane and lowland Chocó ecosystems in a politically stable area.   &#13;Nevertheless, no comprehensive studies have documented the biological diversity along the trail, or anywhere in the Cauca section of the Andean and lowland Chocó, comprising almost 200 linear Km of forest. Plans for linking the lowland Chocó with Munchique and other montane parks in a biological corridor have been presented (Negret et al. 1998), but with the untimely death of the principal researcher, the initiative could lose much of its momentum. There are official (Isaac Bedoya personal communication) projects to expand Munchique National Natural Park's buffering zone into the lower and scientific documentation would greatly enhance the effectiveness of these protective measures.
&#13;The Project&#13;II.1. Justification&#13;The loss of biodiversity -the sixth extinction- is a central crisis amidst the various environmental challenges for the world's human population (Pimm et al. 1995). Prevention of this loss, however, is greatly complicated as many of the biodiversity hotspots of the world are poorly documented, and decisions over priority areas for conservation lack the information necessary to maximize species protected across taxa in a given -often restricted- geographical range (Reid et al. 1993). Since not all  extant forests can be effectively protected, it is imperative to survey potential areas as quickly as possible in order to prioritize ranges and submit biological data relevant to conservation and sustainable development alternatives in areas of human expansion (McNeely 1995, Prance 1995).   &#13;Colombia ranks among the Earth's highest conservation priorities due to its exceedingly high diversity coupled with the threats posed by human development and commercial resource exploitation (McNeely et al. 1990). It is one of the richest countries in terms of species diversity per unit area comprising an estimated 14-15% of the planet's flora and fauna in 0.77% of its surface (CI 1997). Since most plant and animal species have not been documented, particularly in tropical forests (Claridge 1995), the documented diversity of Colombia is expected to increase substantially with further biological inventory work.   &#13;The Colombian Chocó has been recently listed as a frontier under medium to high threat, which means that if ongoing or planned human activities continue, the forests will be significantly degraded (Bryant et al. 1997). Indeed, in the most economically developed province of the Colombian Chocó, Valle del Cauca (from the forest cover data in Bryant et al. 1997), most of the forest is no longer considered frontier because it is largely fragmented, degraded or developed for agriculture. The Chocó area of endemism is of special biological interest because it harbors one of the highest numbers of restricted species, subspecies and genera of plants and animals (Cracraft 1985, Gentry 1982, Lellinger 1975).
&#13;This combination of environmental threats, high endemism and exceptionally high diversity urge the need for inventories that provide data for understanding the origin and history of diversification of life on earth in order to inform decisions related to effective conservation action and resource management (Wheeler 1995). An adequate basic inventory of organisms is hence fundamental to found conservation and sustainable development plans (Prance 1995).
&#13;Conservation Priority&#13;Urgent, it encompasses a hitherto unknown portion of the Chocó Endemic Bird Area regarded as having great biological importance and threat level (Stattersfield et al. 1997). Our survey is adjacent to Munchique (CO 53), an area threatened by colonization, a hydroelectric power project and highway construction (Wege and Long 1995, Dinerstein  1995).&#13;Habitat involved&#13;&#13;Vegetation types vary considerably along the latitudinal gradient between the Atrato river and the Pacific lowlands in the northern section of Esmeraldas, Ecuador; and the altitudinal cross-section bordered by the Pacific Ocean and the West Andes (Stattersfield et al. 1997). Central lowland Chocó is the only place in the neotropics where tropical pluvial forest (sensu Holdridge 1967) occurs (Gentry 1982). This forest exists due to the high year-round rainfall as a result of the moisture-laden air from the Pacific condensing on the Western slope of the Western Andes (Haffer 1970).
&#13;The Uribe trail encompasses sections of lowland tropical wet (0-1000 m; 4000-8000mm precipitation/year), tropical pluvial (thin section of the Andean foothills; more than 8000mm/year), humid lower montane (1000-2300 m; 2000-6000mm/year) and humid pre-montane (above 2300; 4000-6000mm/year) forest (Stattersfield et al. 1997). We intend to conduct our first survey at a lowland tropical locality.    &#13;Threatened Species following IUCN (1994) categories: data base   &#13;BIRDS&#13;The following restricted-range threatened bird species are listed as in range for the Chocó Endemic Bird Area (Stattersfield et al. 1997, Wege and Long 1995): &#13;&#13;Critically endangered:&#13;Turquoise-throated Puffleg Eriocnemis godini&#13;Endangered:&#13;Plumbeous Forest-falcon Micrastur plumbeus&#13;Banded Ground-cuckoo Neomorphus radiolosus&#13;Black-and-Gold Tanager Bangsia melanochlamys&#13;Red-bellied Grackle Hypopyrrhus pyrohypogaster
&#13;Vulnerable:&#13;Baudó Guan Penelope ortoni&#13;Colorful Puffleg Eriocnemis mirabilis&#13;Five-colored Barbet Capito quinticolor&#13;Bicolored Antvireo Dysithamnus occidentalis&#13;Long-wattled Umbrellabird Cephalopterus penduliger&#13;Tanager Finch Oreothraupis arremonops&#13;Gold-ringed Tanager Bangsia aureocincta&#13;Turquoise Dacnis Dacnis hartlaubi&#13;Scarlet-breasted Dacnis Dacnis berlepschi&#13;Chocó Vireo Vireo masteri&#13;
Additionally, forty-five bird species are known to occur only in the Chocó EBA.
&#13;MAMMALS&#13;List of threatened mammals ranging into the Chocó (IUCN 1996):
 &#13;Critically endangered:&#13;[Handley’s] Opossum Marmosops handleyi&#13;Rice Rat Oryzomys gorgasi&#13;
Endangered:&#13;Geoffroy's Spider Monkey Ateles geoffroyi griscescens&#13;Colombian Weasel Mustela felipei&#13;
Vulnerable:&#13;Woolly Opossum Caluromys derbianus&#13;Hog-nosed [Nectar-feeding] Bat Choeroniscus periosus&#13;American [Handley’s] Leaf-nosed Bat Lonchophylla handleyi [this was a misdiagnosis, see Dávalos 2004]&#13;Chocó White-lined Bat Platyrrhinus chocoensis&#13;Night Monkey Aotus lemurinus&#13;Brown-headed Spider Monkey Ateles fusciceps&#13;Capuchin Monkey Cebus capuchinus&#13;Bush Dog Speothos venaticus&#13;Giant Otter Pteronura brasiliensis&#13;Andean Bear Tremarctos ornatus&#13;Baird's Tapir Tapirus bairdii
&#13;This list, nonetheless, reflects the lack of systematic long-term inventory data for the region. Mammalian diversity is richest in the lowland tropical forests and we expect new records as a result of a focused, localized inventory.
&#13;Objectives&#13;Project Aim&#13;To inventory the diversity of mammals and trees at an exceptionally rich Neotropical forest site.
&#13;Reconnaissance trip&#13;To prospect the Uribe trail in its entirety, documenting possibilities of establishing research sites along the route with the aide of the Munchique Park staff.&#13;To select one site along the Uribe trail, preferably in the lowland portion, suitable for long-term studies of the diversity of terrestrial flora and fauna.&#13;First Field season&#13;Document systematically the mammalian, and botanical diversity of the selected site, within a 3-Km ground radius.&#13;To spatially map the tree family, genera and species diversity for the 3-Km radius study site using physically collected data.&#13;Present the result to the MMA (Ministry of the Environment), IVH (Instituto Von Humboldt) and ICN (Instituto de Ciencias Naturales) and local communities; as well as NGO's involved in conservation in the Colombian Chocó&#13;
Subsequent work&#13;Comparison of mammalian diversity with well-documented lowland neotropical sites, such as La Selva, Barro Colorado Island, Paracou, Cosha-Cashu, assessing the exhaustiveness of results&#13;To study the patterns of tree diversity, extrapolating to a wider area using a GIS-based model incorporating botanical inventory information&#13;To test the predicted patterns with field observation and thus calibrate the model. Integration of faunal data into the GIS-diversity model&#13;Spatial mapping of selected endemic species from studied taxa (initially trees) to calibrate the model&#13;Prioritization of research for areas shown to be exceptionally rich by the model.&#13;
Long-term plans&#13;Continued surveys around initial research site, testing the accuracy of the model.&#13;Submission of results to relevant agencies and community instances so that they may establish a management plan based on the information collected from the surveys and the biodiversity model.&#13;
Location&#13;Frontier forest cover showing prospective site from Bryant et al. 1997 [see photo below]. Forests in red are under medium to high threat, forests in ochre are degraded.&#13; &#13;Mammalian Inventory&#13;Site will be selected based on good forest condition as well as topographical characteristics, allowing for microhabitat diversity, without imposing restrictions on access within the 3-Km area. Steep climbs are not only difficult for humans, non-volant mammals avoid them too. Within the 3-Km radius that constitute the selected site, non-standardized observations and standardized collecting, trapping and mist-netting procedures will be performed following Voss and Emmons (1996). To properly document mammalian species diversity, photographic vouchers will be taken when identification problems arise (Simmons and Voss 1998). Specimens will be collected, if it is assessed that uncertainty cannot be resolved by comparing pictures with existing collections. To maximize the biological information derived from each sacrificed animal, tissue samples will be preserved in ethanol and shall be deposited at the Molecular Laboratory of Instituto Von Humboldt, Cali.&#13;All specimens will be deposited at the Instituto de Ciencias Naturales in Bogotá. Members of the team have access to the collections and herbaria at Museo de Ciencias Naturales, Popayán; Universidad del Valle, Cali; ICN, Bogotá; British Museum Natural History, London; Tring, Cambridge and some of the world's largest animal collections at the American Museum of Natural History, New York.   &#13;Biodiversity model&#13;&#13;Extrapolating biodiversity from those areas known and studied to areas unknown is a problem at the heart of biodiversity studies (Colwell and Coddington, 1994). A fast and efficient method of accurate spatial extrapolation at a conservation-relevant scale could prove highly important in conservation planning and forest management. The use of GIS in biodiversity mapping offers great potential in making spatial extrapolation, yet its current application remains limited. Extensive use of GIS has been made in conservation decision support in the Western Ghats of India, where conservation areas are identified as those least under threat from social and economic expansion (Lakshmi et al. 1998; Prasad 1998; Prasad et al. 1998). Similar schemes have been used in Mexico (Bojorqueztapia, 1995), and a gap analysis program (GAP) has been developed running along a similar scheme for monitoring biodiversity (Scott, 1993). A climate-based GIS has been used in Latin America to predict where a specific species of wild bean might occur, with very encouraging results (Jones et al. 1997), but there has been no work using GIS to predict biodiversity, at any level, rather than solely to protect it after extensive field recognition of particularly rich target areas.&#13;The Pattern of Biodiversity Model (PBM) aims to use physical factors including climate, topography, resource availability and soil conditions to extrapolate the floral and faunal diversity from the 3km study radius, to the a larger scale in the Chocó. The PBM planned for this project, would be a break through in conservation planning and biodiversity assessment. Further analysis could look at the validity of extrapolating the algorithms from the Chocó region to other areas of montane and lowland forest.
&#13;Institutions and Personnel&#13;The biodiversity survey of the Uribe trail is an independent student-based project, with technical and scientific assistance from:
&#13;Mammalogy Department at AMNH (American Museum of Natural History), New York&#13;CERC (Center for Environmental Research and Conservation) consortium at Columbia University, New York&#13;HERB Project at the Geography Department at King's College, London&#13; And the students involved are:  &#13;Liliana M. Dávalos&#13;Andrew Jarvis &#13; Map from Bryant et al (1997), pictures taken by Liliana Dávalos except Liliana by T. Donegan and Andrew by D. Davison.
&#13;References&#13;Bojorqueztapia LA, Azuara I, Ezcurra E, Floresvillela O, (1995) Identifying conservation priorities in Mexico through geographic information-systems and modelling, Ecological Applications, Vol.5, No.1, pp.215-231.
Bryant, D., Nielsen, D. and L. Tangley (1997) The last frontier forests -Ecosystems and economies on the edge. WRI Forest Frontiers Initiative 
Chapman, F. M. (1917) The distribution of bird-life in Colombia, Bull. Amer. Mus. Nat. Hist. 36, 1-729 
CI (1997) Megadiversity, Conservation International 
CIESIN (1998) Unsmoothed map of world population density. 
Claridge, M.F. (1995) Introducing Systematics Agenda 2000, Biod. Cons. 4, 451-454
Colwell, R.K. and J.A. Coddington (1994) Estimating terrestrial biodiversity through extrapolation. Phil. Trans. R. Soc. Lond B 345, 101-118 
Cracraft, J. (1985) Historical Biogeography and patterns of differentiation within South American Avifauna: areas of endemism, Orni. Monog. 36, 49-84 
Dinerstein, E.  (1995) A conservation assessment of terrestrial ecoregions in Latin America and the Caribbean, World Bank 
EcoLógica (1992) Cover of the february issue. 
Gentry, A.H. (1982) Phytogeographic patterns as evidence for a Chocó refuge, pp 112-136 in Prance, G.T. (1982) ed. Biological Diversification in the Tropics. Columbia Univ. Press
Gentry, A.H. (1993) A field guide to the families and genera of Woody plants of Northwest South America, CI 
Haffer, J (1970) Geologic-climatic history and zoogeographic significance of the Urabá region in northwestern Colombia, Caldasia 10,603-636 
Holdridge, L.R. (1967) Life Zone Ecology, San José, Costa Rica: Tropical Science Center
IUCN (1996) IUCN Red List of Threatened Animals, IUCN 
IVH (1997) Bio-Diversidad: mapa de prioridades de conservación en Colombia, IVH 
Jones PG, Beebe SE, Tohme J, and NW Galwey (1997) The use of geographical information systems in biodiversity exploration and conservation, Biodiversity and Conservation, Vol.6, no.7, pp.947-958. 
Lakshmi VU, Murthy MSR, and CBS Dutt (1998) Efficient forest resource management through GIS and remote sensing, Current Science, Vol.75, No.3, pp.272-282. 
Lellinger, D.B. (1975) A phytogeographic analysis of Chocó pterydophytes, Fern Gaz. 11, 105-114 
McNeely, J.A. (1995) Keep all the pieces: Systematics 2000 and world conservation, Biod. Cons. 4(5), 510-19 
Negret, A.J. et al. (1998) Proyecto Corredor Naya [PDF is Shepardson et al. 2002] 
Offerman, H.L., Dale, V.H., Pearson, S.M., Bierregard, R.O. and R.V. O'Neill 1995 Effects of fragmentation on Neotropical fauna: current research and data availability. Environmentalist 3, 191-211 
Olson D.M. and E. Dinerstein 1997 Global 200: conserving the world's distinctive Ecoregions, WWF-US 
Pimm, S.L. et al. (1995) The future of Biodiversity, Science 269,347-50  Prance, G.T. (1995) Systematics, conservation and sustainable development, Biod. Cons 4, 490-500 
Redford, K.H and Mansour, J.A. eds. (1996) Traditional peoples and biodiversity conservation in large tropical landscapes, America Verde Pubs. TNC 
Reid, W.V. 1993 Biodiversity indicators for policy-makers, WRI 
Scott JM, Davis F, Csuti B, Noss R, Butterfield B, Groves C, Anderson H, Caicco S, Derchia F, Edwards TC, Ulliman J, and RG Wright (1993) Gap Analysis - A geographic approach to protection of biological diversity, Wildlife Monographs, No.123, pp.1-41. 
Simmons, N.B. and R.S. Voss 1998 The mammals of Paracou, French Guiana: a neotropical lowland rainforest fauna. Part 1: Bats Bull. Amer. Mus. Nat. Hist. 237 
Stattersfield et al. (1997) Endemic Bird Areas of the World: Priorities for biodiversity Conservation, Birdlife Conservation Series, Birdlife International 
UniValle 1994 Memorias del 1er Congreso Colombiano de Biodiversidad, Diciembre 1994, Cali, Universdad del Valle 
Voss, R.S. and L.H. Emmons 1996 Mammalian diversity in neotropical lowland rainforests: a preliminary assessment Bull. Amer. Mus. Nat. Hist. 230 
Wege, D.C. and Long, A, J. (1995) Key areas for threatened birds in the Neotropics, BirdLife Conservation Series No. 5. BirdLife International 
Western, D and Wright, R.M. (1995) The background to community-based conservation in
Western, D and Wright, R.M. 1995 eds. Natural Connections: perspectives in community-based conservation, Island Press 
Wheeler, Q.D. (1995) Systematics, the scientific basis for inventories of biodiversity, Biod. &amp; Cons. 4, 476-489 </description>
    <item>
      <title>Lowland forest outside Guapi, Colombia</title>
      <link>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito.html#0</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">bda2259c-0a98-48d7-bfc1-0a9de7800eaa</guid>
      <enclosure url="http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/forest/forest.jpg" length="13876" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/forest/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/forest/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/forest/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;Lowland forest outside Guapi, Colombia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>View of the West Andes from the Munchique cabin</title>
      <link>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito.html#1</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">63efa22d-22ac-435f-b944-84c2be6e4e71</guid>
      <enclosure url="http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/trail/trail.jpg" length="9599" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/trail/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/trail/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/trail/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;View of the West Andes from the Munchique cabin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Canopy at Guapi</title>
      <link>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito.html#2</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">bc140f2f-b3b1-4356-b2ec-81fc4f06cd96</guid>
      <enclosure url="http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/canopy/canopy.jpg" length="52296" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/canopy/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/canopy/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/canopy/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;Canopy at Guapi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Another view in Guapi</title>
      <link>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito.html#3</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">11526a6c-1c83-4305-9ca5-8b028023c6ff</guid>
      <enclosure url="http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/canopy2/canopy2.jpg" length="15220" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/canopy2/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/canopy2/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/canopy2/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;Another view in Guapi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Club-winged manakin, Machaeropterus deliciosus </title>
      <link>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito.html#4</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">6b896da7-243d-4fa5-a79a-f96d29e9e18a</guid>
      <enclosure url="http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/manakin/manakin.jpg" length="10335" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/manakin/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/manakin/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/manakin/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;Club-winged manakin, &lt;span class=&quot;style_2&quot;&gt;Machaeropterus deliciosus &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small Artibeus captured at Tambito</title>
      <link>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito.html#5</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">fce726b1-99d8-4a57-b8dc-aa976afb4181</guid>
      <enclosure url="http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/cutebat/cutebat.jpg" length="71603" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/cutebat/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/cutebat/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/cutebat/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;Small &lt;span class=&quot;style_2&quot;&gt;Artibeus&lt;/span&gt; captured at Tambito&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Frontier forest zoom on Colombia</title>
      <link>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito.html#6</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">8ba76275-96ed-4b5d-8e37-f131aa572e37</guid>
      <enclosure url="http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/map1/map1.jpg" length="18434" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/map1/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/map1/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/map1/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;Frontier forest zoom on Colombia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lowlands of Tambito</title>
      <link>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito.html#7</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">35b34c63-85fe-4f1f-bfb9-d65d8f6b4b68</guid>
      <enclosure url="http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/lowland/lowland.jpg" length="32214" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/lowland/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/lowland/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/lowland/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;Lowlands of Tambito&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Liliana Dávalos,1999</title>
      <link>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito.html#8</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">a5c4e720-61a3-4b7d-9f37-729cd06a046c</guid>
      <enclosure url="http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/Liliana/Liliana.jpg" length="99851" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/Liliana/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/Liliana/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/Liliana/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;Liliana Dávalos,1999&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tambito</title>
      <link>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito.html#9</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">1bccc385-1605-4b92-ad5f-057067a2a34e</guid>
      <enclosure url="http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/tambito1/tambito1.jpg" length="199573" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/tambito1/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/tambito1/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/tambito1/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;Tambito&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Andy Jarvis, 1999</title>
      <link>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito.html#10</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">de8627bb-bce2-4ac3-bbfd-602e10e92475</guid>
      <enclosure url="http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/jarvis/jarvis.jpg" length="11285" type="image/jpeg"/>
      <iphoto:thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/jarvis/thumb.jpg</iphoto:thumbnail>
      <iweb:micro>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/jarvis/micro.jpg</iweb:micro>
      <iweb:mip-thumbnail>http://www.lmdavalos.net/Site/Site/TravelPages/Pages/Tambito_files/Media/jarvis/mip.jpg</iweb:mip-thumbnail>
      <iweb:richTitle>&lt;div style=&quot;padding: 0px; &quot; class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default_External_0_0&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;image_cluster_layout_style_default&quot;&gt;&lt;p style=&quot;padding-bottom: 0pt; padding-top: 0pt; &quot; class=&quot;Caption&quot;&gt;Andy Jarvis, 1999&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</iweb:richTitle>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
