<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>evolution | Dávalos Lab</title>
    <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/tag/evolution/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://lmdavalos.github.io/tag/evolution/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>evolution</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://lmdavalos.github.io/media/icon_hud44501404c914d67889d8518d1a662c7_303770_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>evolution</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/tag/evolution/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phyllostomid Bats: A unique Mammalian Radiation</title>
      <link>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/edited_books_phyllostomid_bats/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lmdavalos.github.io/publication/edited_books_phyllostomid_bats/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With over two-hundred species distributed across most of mainland Mexico, Central and South America, and islands in the Caribbean Sea, the Phyllostomidae bat family (American leaf-nosed bats) is one of the world’s most diverse mammalian families in terms of its trophic, or feeding, diversity. From an insectivorous ancestry, extant species have evolved into several dietary classes, including blood-feeding, vertebrate carnivory, and the consumption of nectar, pollen, and fruit, in a period of about 30 million years. Phyllostomid plant-visiting species are responsible for pollinating over five-hundred species of neotropical shrubs, trees, vines, and epiphytes—many of which are economically and ecologically important—and they also disperse the seeds of at least another five-hundred plant species. Fruit-eating and seed-dispersing members of this family thus play a crucial role in the regeneration of neotropical forests, and the fruit eaters are among the most abundant mammals in these habitats.
Coauthored by leading experts in the field and synthesizing the latest advances in molecular biology and ecological methods, Phyllostomid Bats is the first overview in more than forty years of the evolution of the many morphological, behavioral, physiological, and ecological adaptations in this family. Featuring abundant illustrations as well as details on the current classification and conservation status of phyllostomid species, it is both a comprehensive reference for these ecologically vital mammals and a fascinating exploration of the evolutionary process of adaptive radiation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
